<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Daniel Muñoz Lozano</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Daniel Muñoz Lozano</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 10:40:15 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://danielml.mx/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Herramientas y programas que uso</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/herramientas-y-programas-que-uso/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 10:40:15 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/herramientas-y-programas-que-uso/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/herramientas-y-programas-que-uso/screenshot-020225-111003.png" alt="Featured image of post Herramientas y programas que uso" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dejo aquí una lista de lo que uso cotidianamente. En general priorizo programas libres, ligeros, rápidos y estéticos que sigan la &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_philosophy&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;filosofía de UNIX&lt;/a&gt;, mientras que para &lt;em&gt;hardware&lt;/em&gt; busco que puedan cumplir con varios propósitos. Esto significa que aquí no vas a ver nada restrictivo y gordo como las Macs, Windows, Adobe Reader, Chrome, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todos estos programas se encuentra o en los repositorios oficiales de Arch o en el AUR. Además, puedes consultar los archivos de configuración que uso con muchos estos programas en mi GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hardware&#34;&gt;Hardware
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computadora:&lt;/strong&gt; ThinkPad L13 Yoga Gen 2 con un procesador 11th Gen Intel i5-1145G7 (8) @ 4.400GHz
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Esta laptop es lo más cercano que he encontrado a una laptop perfecta. Incluye un trackpoint, una pantalla táctil con pluma y un factor de forma ligero, aunque desearía que fuera tan sólo un poco más pequeña la relación de aspecto, algo así como la X200 clásica, y además como muchas laptops modernas las opciones de mejora son limitadas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;software&#34;&gt;Software
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sistema operativo:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://artixlinux.org&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Artix Linux&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Linux sin SystemD. En realidad sólo lo uso porque me quiero sentir especial y diferente al resto de los usuarios de Arch, pero es básicamente lo mismo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manejador de ventanas:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://dwm.suckless.org&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;dwm&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/danielml-mx/dwm&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Fork personal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hace mucho tiempo utilizaba KDE y me pareció el mejor entorno de escritorio de las opciones disponibles. También he intentado Wayland, particularmente hyprland, pero no me parece que esté suficientemente desarrollado todavía.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compositor:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/yshui/picom&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;picom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/PipeWire&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;PipeWire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminal:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://st.suckless.org/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;st&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shell:&lt;/strong&gt; zsh
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No utilizo ohmyzsh, sino he instalado los plugins de autocomplete, autosuggestions y syntax-highlighting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editor de texto:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://neovim.io/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;neovim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Navegador de archivos:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/sxyazi/yazi&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;yazi&lt;/a&gt; con &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/jstkdng/ueberzugpp&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;ueberzugpp&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Antes usaba &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/gokcehan/lf&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;lf&lt;/a&gt; con UB, y me sigue agradando bastante como programa pues, a diferencia de yazi, no intenta reimplementar tareas que deben delegarse a otros programas. Aun así, yazi simplemente tiene más capacidades de personalización y extensibilidad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Navegador web:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://librewolf.net/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;LibreWolf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fork de Firefox orientada a la privacidad y seguridad, aunque debo admitir que algunas de las funcionalidades que esperas de la web moderna no siempre funcionan con LibreWolf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualizador de documentos:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/ahrm/sioyek&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;sioyek&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anteriormente utilizaba zathura (&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d6zodqSFN60&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;video&lt;/a&gt;), sin embargo se volvió bastante inestable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualizador de imágenes:&lt;/strong&gt; sxiv&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daemon de notificaciones:&lt;/strong&gt; dunst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Apología católica: refutaciones a argumentos comunes</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/apologia-catolica/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 20:23:13 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/apologia-catolica/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lo que procede es un repositorio de argumentos comunes en contra del catolicismo acompañados cada uno de una refutación definitiva, así como fuentes adicionales para quienes estén interesados en profundizar sobre dichas refutaciones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
### Contra el cristianismo

***

--&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;contra-el-catolicismola-iglesia-católica&#34;&gt;Contra el catolicismo/la Iglesia católica
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Iglesia católica y el catolicismo, dado que históricamente han sido el cuerpo de creyentes y de cristianos más grande en el mundo, son frecuente objeto de críticas tanto de no creyentes como de cristianos no católicos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;el-catolicismo-es-la-religión-que-más-ha-matado&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El catolicismo es la religión que más ha matado&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Este argumento, que a veces se presenta también como una crítica hacia la Iglesia católica, frecuentemente se &amp;ldquo;justifica&amp;rdquo; por las cruzadas y/o las inquisiciones. En realidad, el discurso popular sobre cómo operaron estas dos campañas está muy equivocado y lleno de mitos, producto de un currículum educativo que busca pintar la era medieval como &amp;ldquo;la era oscura&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Comenzando por las cruzadas, ... --&gt;
&lt;!-- Por otro lado, --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuando se habla de las inquisiciones bajo el contexto del discurso popular, frecuentemente se presenta esta idea de que estas campañas estuvieron llenas de juicios arbitrarios, tortura y gente quemada en la hoguera. La realidad no podría ser más diferente. La tarea principal de los inquisidores no era hacer sufrir a herejes, sino intentar salvar su alma y preservar así la unión de la Iglesia. Además, los juicios a los que eran sometidos los imputados eran extremadamente complejos, para nada arbitrarios, con sus propias reglas y procedimientos no del todo diferentes a las de nuestros juicios modernos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Para los imputados que llegaban a ser declarados como herejes, las sanciones aplicadas a través de los procedimientos inquisitivos medievales eran de índole penitente, no punitivo. Por ejemplo, el Tribunal del Santo Oficio, la institución que llevó a cabo la famosa Inquisición española, además de que no detenía a quienes se retractaban, aplicaba sanciones como asistir a misa con un cirio encendido en la mano junto con la realización de ayunos, el rezo de oraciones y el pago de multas para la blasfemia leve y auto de fe con soga al cuello y mordaza en la boca más la aplicación de cien azotes o el destierro para la blasfemia grave. Tanto el castigo corporal como el exilio forzado pueden sonar duros, sin embargo estos castigos eran más benignos a comparación de aquellos aplicados por las autoridades civiles, los cuales incluían desde la mutilación de la lengua hasta la pena de muerte. Hablando de, cabe destacar que los inquisidores no podían sentenciaban a muerte, sino que debían entregar a los herejes más persistentes a las autoridades seculares. Sobre todo, cabe destacar que las instituciones de la Inquisición eran aquellas más interesadas en el bien del hereje, a diferencia de los laicos, quienes sólo querían deshacerse del hereje antes de que la comunidad sufriera, y de los tribunales judiciales seculares, los cuales sólo buscaban castigar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incluso la Inquisición española, considerada popularmente la más celosa de todas, aun reconociendo el gran antisemitismo que la manchó y que culminó en la expulsión de los judíos del territorio español, hecho inconsistente con los principios de la Iglesia católica y por el cual Juan Pablo II se ha disculpado, fue acreedora de aproximadamente 3,000 muertes desde 1550 a 1800, las cuales desde luego son injustificables, mas demuestran un panorama muy diferente de la historia del que se presenta en el discurso popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lectura adicional&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peters, E. (1988). &lt;em&gt;Inquisition&lt;/em&gt;. Free Press. (principalmente pp. 64 - 67, 87)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.congreso.gob.pe/Docs/participacion/museo/Inquisicion/files/delitos-juzgados1.pdf&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Delitos juzgados por el Tribunal de la Inquisición&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carta al Card. Roger Etchegaray con motivo de la publicación de las Actas del Congreso Internacional sobre la Inquisición&lt;/em&gt;. (15 de junio de 2004). La Santa Sede. &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.vatican.va/content/john-paul-ii/es/letters/2004/documents/hf_jp-ii_let_20040615_simposio-inquisizione.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://www.vatican.va/content/john-paul-ii/es/letters/2004/documents/hf_jp-ii_let_20040615_simposio-inquisizione.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;yo-sólo-sigo-la-palabra-de-dios-no-las-tradiciones-de-los-hombres&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yo sólo sigo la Palabra de Dios, no las tradiciones de los hombres&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;La idea de que la fe cristiana es algo que se puede interpretar sólo a través de la escritura es un precursor a la racionalización de varios aspectos de nuestra sociedad. Si padeces de monocromatismo, pero estudias arduamente el color rojo y las propiedades del espectro de luz visible que lo constituyen, ¿realmente sabes lo que es el color rojo? ¿Es lo mismo leer y hasta ver fotos de Río de Janeiro que visitarlo? En un sentido epistemológico, sería difícil concluir que estos dos objetos de estudio se pueden conocer exclusivamente a través de las facultades lógico-racionales del ser humano. De la misma manera, el verdadero cristianismo (y la religión en general) no es algo que se comprende al creerlo tanto como se comprende al vivirlo, y como católicos debemos de vivirlo de la manera que Cristo nos enseñó, cosa que no hizo a través de libros, sino a través de sus obras, las cuales hoy hemos instituido como tradición. Sólo observa los desarrollos en las &amp;ldquo;iglesias&amp;rdquo; que, por tomar la escritura como fuente única de revelación, han abandonado la tradición.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por otro lado, este argumento viene cargado de una desconfianza inherente hacia el prójimo. A fin de ahorrarme una larga explicación hago la siguiente pregunta: si Cristo le confió las llaves de su Iglesia a un hombre, ¿bajo qué autoridad desconfías tú de ellos?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Purgatorio, Dante Alighieri (John Ciardi Translation) - Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/purgatorio-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:39:48 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/purgatorio-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021. Más que una crítica o reseña del poema, es un intento de vendérselo al público general. Me da un poco de cringe el estilo con el cual escribía antes, pero igual decido publicarla. Más importante, evité ahondar en el tema de la religión para hacer la publicación más acogedora para el público general, algo que nunca haría hoy.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---
#![Purgatorio, Dante
#Alighieri](../assets/purgatorio_dante.jpg){.titleimg}
--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Expect no more of me in word or deed: here your will is upright,
free, and whole, and you would be in error not to heed whatever your
own impulse prompts you to: lord of yourself I crown and mitre you.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Dante Alighieri, &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dante&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt; was written in 1320, and 700 years later its
ability to comprehensively cover all of human experience within a single
narrative remains unmatched. Drawing from the teachings of Thomas
Aquinas in his &lt;em&gt;Summa Theologiae&lt;/em&gt;, Dante outlines the universe as a
sphere, one in which God is its circumference and Satan its center.
Thus, the value of any given thing can be determined simply by
establishing how close it is to the boundaries of the sphere, and how
far away it is from its center. But this model is much more than that,
and its genius lies in the fact that it is capable of covering the order
of the literal universe, Christian experience and morality all within a
single model, outlined from the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;. It deals
with the physical understanding of the world, since (under the Ptolemaic
system of the times) the Earth was the center of the universe, which
meant that Hell was the origin point of the universe. It deals with
Christianity, because it takes Readers through the recognition of sin
(&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;), its complete rejection (&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;), and the soul&#39;s
ascent to God (&lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;). It deals with morality, because it explores
questions like what makes a bad man and what does it take to become a
good man. Above all, the &lt;em&gt;Commedia&lt;/em&gt; is comprehensive, since it manages
to encompass so much of what it means to be human, regardless of whether
these were born in antiquity, the Middle Ages, or the twenty-first
century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they climb the two ledges and seven cornices to reach the Earthly
Paradise, we yet again see all kinds of human faults, sometimes even on
par with what was found in the flames below, except these sinners
acknowledge, regret, and repent their mistakes, something which will
ultimately guarantee them an entrance into Paradise, no matter how
wicked their previous actions might have been. They suffer, but their
suffering stems from purification, which is temporary, not damnation,
which is eternal. Seeing all this pain, Dante (through Virgil) takes the
time to explain his theory on the nature of sin, in which he theorizes
all sin really stems from love: the Proud, Envious, and Wrathful have
corrupted their love of themselves to hate of others; the Slothful have
loved too little; and the Avaricious, Gluttonous, and Lustful have loved
immoderately. To reject sin, then, is to love truly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first steps are always the hardest, but as Dante distances himself
from the Earth and climbs the mountain by rejecting sin and taking in
virtue, his steps become lighter and lighter, until he finally reaches
the Earthly Paradise and prepares himself to rise towards the stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second part to Dante&#39;s great allegory does not disappoint. By now
most of the novelty has worn out and you&#39;re already accustomed to
Dante&#39;s world, style, and exposition, but they don&#39;t really cease to
be captivating. In the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;, through its characters, their
philosophy, and the very design of Purgatory, Dante yet again
demonstrates a side of pre-classical and medieval thought dearly missed
today. It presents a moral commentary on what is wrong, like the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, but it also emphasizes doing what is right. The Christian
roots of the poem are also more emphasized, particularly through the
virtue of the life of Mary, the Beatitudes sung by the Angels, and other
allegorical devices that urge the souls unto good. All in all, the
&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; accomplishes its goal of being a bridge between the
depravity of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; and the beauty of the &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main dynamic here is similar to what is seen in the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;: the
sinners suffer a punishment that relates to their sin. However, in the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; the punishment directly reflected the sin, whereas in the
&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; the punishment reverses the sin. For example, in the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; the Lustful were punished by being violently whirled through
the air, symbolizing how they followed their impulses on a whim. In the
&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; though, their impulses are symbolized by burning flames,
and they achieve penance by learning to stand calmly in them. Likewise,
the filthy marshes of the Styx hindered the Slothful&#39;s movement in the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, but here, they run around the cornice so vigorously that they
won&#39;t even stop to speak to Dante. You must remember Dante has given
symbolic meaning to nearly everything in the &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt;, and
these punishments are certainly no coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; also presents the dynamic of the whip and the rein. As
he climbs each cornice to meet the sinners, Dante is presented first
with a whip that urges the sinners unto emulation of virtue and then
with a reign that deters them from their sin, both symbolizing the same
tools utilized to control the behavior of a horse, respectively. These
devices, though presented in various forms, consist of historical
examples of great human virtue and fault particular to the sin of the
cornice on which the Poets find themselves, and the first examples of
great virtue always come from the life of Mary. For example, when the
Poets reach the first cornice, that of the Proud, they are presented
with three bas-reliefs carved in the perfect marble of the mountain&#39;s
inner cliff, the first of which depicts Mary&#39;s humble reaction upon the
Annunciation. After meeting the Proud and discovering their punishment,
Dante notices that the floor is carved with &lt;em&gt;thirteen&lt;/em&gt; examples of
destruction through pride, notable among these the tale of Arachne and
of Nimrod and his Tower of Babel. It is these devices which most
distinguish the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; from the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;. Hell is a destination
meant only to reflect the pain its inhabitants caused, but Purgatory is
instead a transitory phase, meant to teach and prepare the souls for
salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pleasant surprise within the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; is the fact that it contains
many medieval scientific, philosophical, and metaphysical theories, and
though at times they proved hard to follow to my modern mind, they were
exceptionally insightful. The most important of these is Virgil&#39;s
discourse on love, which as mentioned before is central to Dante&#39;s
understanding of sin. However, there are many other tangential
discourses that, though they aren&#39;t as crucial to the story and some
are even scientifically irrelevant today, they are still quite
thought-provoking. These are unfortunately too long to properly discuss
here, but as a quick overview, the Poets discuss anything from the
metaphysical faults of Averroism and Epicureanism to
Aristotelian/Aquinian ideas on conception and the birth of the human
soul. They greatly enrich the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s historic and cultural
content and yet again demonstrate how, perhaps contrary to popular
belief, the ancients and medievals weren&#39;t all ignorant and backwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-ciardis-translation&#34;&gt;A note on Ciardi&#39;s translation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; proved to be a more difficult read than I had
anticipated. It isn&#39;t incomprehensible by any means, but you do have to
pay extra attention to ensure that you don&#39;t miss out on any of
Dante&#39;s fine-carved details. The way in which the Poets utilize the
stars relative to the southern hemisphere of the world to describe
almost the exact hour of the day was particularly hard to grasp. Were it
not for the help of Ciardi, I certainly wouldn&#39;t have understood these
and other complexities presented in the canticle. Though I haven&#39;t
checked out the other translations, I can definitely vouch for this one.
Both it&#39;s notes and presentation are clear enough, but as with the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, the tone of the poem takes precedence, something I&#39;m
personally fine with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-i-recommend-this-to&#34;&gt;Who I recommend this to
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in morality:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; will yet again
enlighten those who are deeply interested in virtue. The whip is a most
useful compilation of great virtue from all periods of history, and many
other devices in the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; also work as a commentary on virtue. I
invite you to ponder why Dante chose to place the suicide Cato as the
protector of Purgatory, yet Pierre delle Vigne suffers in the seventh
circle of Hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in Christianity:&lt;/strong&gt; As stated, the Christian
influence is more clear in this canticle as opposed to the previous one.
The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; has all sorts of metaphors and references that allude
to Christianity (specifically Roman Catholicism, obviously) and the
history of the Church, from the color of the three steps taken at the
entrance of Purgatory to the Triumphal Chariot and the Heavenly Pageant.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>1984, George Orwell - Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/1984-orwell-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:12:11 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/1984-orwell-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales de 2021.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Sanity is not statistical.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;George Orwell, &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; even need an introduction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year is 1984. Three totalitarian super-states have divided the world
among themselves. Oceania, the Western super-state, includes the
war-torn city of London, home to Winston Smith. As a member of the
Ministry of Truth, he alters historical records to coincide with
whatever the Party desires. To the outside world, he is just another
obedient pawn. On the inside, however, Winston doubts. In a society
omnipresent with telescreens and the mighty Big Brother, Winston knows
he&#39;s doomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A classic I have waited far too long to read, &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; does not
disappoint. Though it presents an all-around outstanding plot, it is the
real-life context behind the novel which I find more fascinating. The
hopelessness of the war and post-war eras is clearly presented in the
general unwillingness of the characters to think deeply about complex
matters, but that does not mean Orwell meant for &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; to be a direct
prediction of where this trajectory would lead us, much less another
cautionary tale on communism, contrary to what many took it for. After
all, Orwell himself, as a democratic socialist, was pretty left-leaning.
In reality, while the novel was in some senses inspired by the
atrocities of Stalin, its primary political focus is to discuss the
phenomenon of power. Orwell knew that what once was valid criticism
against the inequalities and atrocities of capitalism had become a cheap
tactic for politicians to prey on the misery and desperation of the
masses so as to gain popularity and, ultimately, power. Hitler did it,
Stalin did it, and Oceania does it. &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; is merely an exaggeration of
this form of manipulation applied on a global scale and projected into
the future, meant to relate Orwell&#39;s concerns to the world. That, at
least in part, is a timeless message, and relates a concern we should
still be on the lookout for even today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I can&#39;t really talk about my favorite part of the novel
without spoiling the plot, but once you get to this part, you&#39;ll
realize this too: the plot doesn&#39;t even really matter. Even now, as
most people know at least the general details of the story of &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;
perhaps without having read it, the book is still worth a read. The real
horror of &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; is found in the way Orwell toys with your perception of
the inner machinations of the Party. The fact that he doesn&#39;t spend too
much time presenting the Party actually works in favor of &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;, as the
lack of information preys on the reader&#39;s fears and ideas about how
ruthlessly totalitarian a government would have to be to reach the level
of power the Party has reached. Is the Party fallible? We may never
determine it with certainty, but a good place to start would be the
first few pages of the novel, if you know what I mean. &lt;em&gt;Al chile ni yo me acuerdo por qué jajajaj.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I can talk about, at least generally, is Winston Smith. The story
is told mostly through his own thoughts, not dialogue, which, again,
actually works in favor of the novel. The narrative style feels
remarkably intimate and personal, completely removed from the orthodoxy
of his environment and, at times, even of his own actions. I think we
can all relate to a moment in our lives in which we took a hard look at
a particular well-accepted attitude of our society, perhaps a
crowd-pleasing fad or an out-of-date tradition, and said &amp;quot;This isn&#39;t
right,&amp;quot; but decided that looking like the odd one out would be too much
of a hassle, so we just quietly acted as would be expected from us.
Winston&#39;s life is this moment constantly in repeat, his actions
betraying his own thoughts over and over again for the sake of safety.
This is most apparent in his conversation with his friend Syme, who
Winston recognizes is smarter than the rest and, though he never finds
direct evidence, knows about Winston&#39;s heterodox thoughts. It creates a
tension that makes you wonder whether or not Winston will ever become
rebellious enough to falter when dissimulating, thus making his facade
visible to the rest, including the dreaded Thought Police, a situation
perhaps allegorical to our ever more close-minded world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; has proved to be timelessly relevant. You may find the lying
&amp;quot;Ministry of Truth&amp;quot; and the torturous &amp;quot;Ministry of Love&amp;quot; silly, but
I know you know about the vulnerabilities kept secret by the &amp;quot;National
Security Agency&amp;quot; and the suppression at Tiananmen at the hands of the
&amp;quot;People&#39;s Liberation Army.&amp;quot; There have always been and perhaps will
always be people who will take us all for fools and try to use us to
gain and remain in power. We won&#39;t prevent their success by keeping our
concerns to ourselves and hoping for things to change, as Winston Smith
did. If we truly wish to live in a free society, we must realize that no
politician or public figure can save us, even those we believe most in.
We can&#39;t expect the government or corporations or Oceania or the
Brotherhood to place our best interests atop their priority list. In
reality, it is and will forever be only up to us to save ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-i-recommend-this-to&#34;&gt;Who I recommend this to
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in politics:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; is a must read for anyone who
wishes to truly understand contemporary politics. Hopefully it&#39;ll also
put into perspective what real totalitarianism looks like and will
prompt you to defend yourself against it at its first sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in modern classics:&lt;/strong&gt; You&#39;ve probably read this
already if you identify with this description, but to those who
haven&#39;t, I trust you will not be disappointed. You will certainly get
to see a lot 20th-century influences on the story and background of
&lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Inferno, Dante Alighieri (John Ciardi Translation) - Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/inferno-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 23:50:11 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/inferno-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/inferno-thoughts/inferno_dante.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Inferno, Dante Alighieri (John Ciardi Translation) - Thoughts" /&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021. Más que una crítica o reseña del poema, es un intento de vendérselo al público general. Me da un poco de cringe el estilo con el cual escribía antes, pero igual decido publicarla. Más importante, evité ahondar en el tema de la religión para hacer la publicación más acogedora para el público general, algo que nunca haría hoy.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;But the stars that marked our starting fall away. We must go deeper
into greater pain, for it is not permitted that we stay.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Dante Alighieri, &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dante&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt; was written in 1320, and 700 years later its
ability to comprehensively cover all of human experience within a single
narrative remains unmatched. Drawing from the teachings of Thomas
Aquinas in his &lt;em&gt;Summa Theologiae&lt;/em&gt;, Dante outlines the universe as a
sphere, one in which God is its circumference and Satan its center.
Thus, the value of any given thing can be determined simply by
establishing how close it is to the boundaries of the sphere, and how
far away it is from its center. But this model is much more than that,
and its genius lies in the fact that it is capable of covering the order
of the literal universe, Christian experience, and morality all within a
single model, outlined from the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;. It deals
with the physical understanding of the world, since (under the Ptolemaic
system of the times) the Earth was the center of the universe, which
meant that Hell was the origin point of the universe. It deals with
Christianity, because it takes Readers through the recognition of sin
(&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;), its complete rejection (&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;), and the soul&#39;s
ascent to God (&lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;). It deals with morality, because it explores
questions like what makes a bad man and what does it take to become a
good man. Above all, the &lt;em&gt;Commedia&lt;/em&gt; is comprehensive, since it manages
to encompass so much of what it means to be human, regardless of whether
these lived in antiquity, the Middle Ages or the twenty-first century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this model in mind, it is the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; which presents the
universe&#39;s damnation and wretches, that which is closest to the center.
Too involved in terrestrial affairs and thus found guilty of &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;,
Dante first finds himself helpless in the Dark Wood of Error. With the
help of his guide, Virgil the poet, he must venture into the Nine
Circles of Hell to know what it truly means to sin, so that he can later
know how to reject it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a journey that covers all faults in human behavior, and
the brilliance of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; (and of the &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt; as a
whole) is the fact that Dante does so by example, relating to the past,
present and future of humanity. He comments on the sins of historical
figures like Ulysses and Alexander the Great. He talks with Farinata on
the state of Florentine politics and its everlasting conflicts. He
cautions Pope Boniface VIII on the fate that awaits him and others like
him were they to continue perverting the holiness of the church. Through
the Nine Circles, each of these figures is masterfully placed according
to Dante&#39;s universal sphere, which itself comments on their moral
value. The &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, then, is an organization of all wrong that men do.
It is the journey of Dante, yes, but the true goal of Dante (the
narrator) is to take &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; on the same journey, so that you too can
learn to recognize and reject the wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; has been a teacher to me. Generally I think people do know
how the people of the Middle Ages lived and died, including myself, but
it wasn&#39;t until after the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; that I began to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;
they lived the way they did. From the faint light in Dark Wood of Error
to the perversion of the Holy Trinity in the ninth and final circle of
Hell, Dante has packed the poem with all sorts of metaphors, symbols and
historical references that reveal to the modern Reader what went on
inside the heads of medieval men, including both the sharpest minds and
the average peasants&#39;. In essence, most people who have not read the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; can expect to have their views on Christianity, morality,
antiquity and the Middle Ages built anew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By categorizing sin into a set of nine descending circles, Dante draws a
critique on the darker side of morality, on what is irrefutably wrong,
even outside of Christian doctrine. It is a critique I learned a lot
from, and think many could benefit from too. Most of all, this
categorization of sin from worse to worst allows us not to learn, but to
&lt;strong&gt;recognize&lt;/strong&gt; what we already know deep down: we are all capable of
enacting great evil, including you, me, and your average Joes and Janes.
The poem forces you to recognize all sorts of evils, sometimes those
that you yourself have not only enacted, but taken pleasure in doing so.
One must, however, attune themselves to the medieval understanding of
evil, which for them was individual and personal, not entirely
collective and based upon how harmful an action is towards others.
Gluttony, for example, often harms no one other than the perpetrator,
yet it is still an evil action. Likewise, methodical fraud is found
below incontinent violence in Hell because it involves a greater usage
of free will. Crime (the modern moral compass) involves destruction. Sin
involves first and foremost self-destruction. In the end, all evil we
enact is only ever reflected unto ourselves, and Dante makes a clear
point that this is true in both life and afterlife, not merely a matter
of divine punishment. The Law of Hell dictates that it is the sinners
who in life have &lt;strong&gt;voluntarily chosen&lt;/strong&gt; their own eternal suffering.
Thus, as they harmed themselves in life, they harm themselves eternally
in the afterlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How this Law manifests itself throughout the poem is perhaps the richest
and most stimulating metaphor in the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, especially because Dante
utilizes real or mythological figures to devise clever punishments that
reflect on the nature of the sinners&#39; sin. Take, for example, the
Violent Against Neighbor, found in the seventh circle of Hell. Their
torment is that they are thrown into a river of boiling blood, symbol of
the blood they spilled in the physical world. Yet not all suffer
equally, for every sinner&#39;s suffering is perfectly attuned to their
wretchedness. The pettier get to be only ankle deep in the river, while
the bloodthirsty like Alexander the Great drown with the blood up to
their eyelashes. Dante&#39;s clever punishments keep you on the edge,
curious to know how the sins of the sinners will turn on them and become
their punishment. You know now how the violent are punished, but how do
you suppose lustful have their sin reflected on them? The gluttonous?
The greedy? Your interest is piqued, isn&#39;t it, Reader?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, while there is great value in the references to great
historical figures such as Alexander, Cleopatra and Caesar, there is
something equally charming about Dante&#39;s more personal references to
the characters of his Florence. Every medieval character Dante meets has
a story to tell, one that places us right in Dante&#39;s time and allows us
to learn more about how different the world was back then. Sometimes you
get to learn about the politics of the time, like stereotypes of the
city of Bologna being one of panderers and seducers and Lucca, of
grafters, and others you get to learn about the personal lives of its
people, like the woeful tale of Ugolino and his death, but they all
allow you to get a sense of what life was like in the then-present, of
who were the people of the Medieval Ages and what they stood (and fell)
for. The &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s masterful presentation of antiquity, morality and
Christianity already made it rich in substance, but these more personal
references make the poem that much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know my writing could never do the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; the justice it deserves,
so while I&#39;m about to be more specific with whom I recommend the poem
to in a moment, I actually think anyone can benefit from reading the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;. The past is truly an alien civilization, its wisdom is almost
completely disconnected from modern thought and is, in many ways, simply
better than it. I am of the belief that the seeds of our future are sown
in our past, and the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; is yet another reason to believe it to be
so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-ciardis-translation&#34;&gt;A note on Ciardi&#39;s translation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Ciardi&#39;s translation in particular, I can vouch for its quality and
do highly recommend it, though it would be imprudent to compare it to
other translations without having read these. I will say, however, that
from the quick research I did before choosing this version, Ciardi&#39;s
translation appears to prioritize the poem&#39;s phonetics over its literal
translation when compared to others and also stands out for its notes. I
can attest to both of these facts, as though I&#39;m used to prose and may
have felt a bit disoriented at times, the poem&#39;s beauty is always
clearly front and center, and any misinterpretation is always cleared up
in the excellent notes anyways. In any case, the particular quirks
between translations aren&#39;t as important as it is to actually read any
version of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; (and the &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt;, for that matter).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-i-recommend-this-to&#34;&gt;Who I recommend this to
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in morality and religion:&lt;/strong&gt; It comes as no surprise
that these readers are often the first to pick up the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;. Rest
assured, this poem has a lot to teach you about zeal, morality, and
their dark counterparts, and you will undoubtedly benefit from its
wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in history:&lt;/strong&gt; There is something special about
getting to see Julius Caesar, Homer, Socrates, Cleopatra and many other
historical figures within the same narrative. History aficionados will
undoubtedly enjoy reading Dante&#39;s profound knowledge on the subject
throughout the pages of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, perhaps learning a thing or two
along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>On Modern Incontinence</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/on-modern-incontinence/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 23:32:51 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/on-modern-incontinence/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/on-modern-incontinence/tinbergen.png" alt="Featured image of post On Modern Incontinence" /&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021. Me da un poco de cringe el estilo con el cual escribía antes, pero igual decido publicarla.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-ethology&#34;&gt;From ethology...
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 1940s, scientist Niko Tinbergen conducted several experiments on
the behavior of herring gulls. Adult herring gulls have a red dot on
their beaks, and newborn herring gulls will peck this dot to ask their
mother to regurgitate food. In one of his experiments, he designed a
fake cardboard beak, completely detached from a body, and offered it to
the chicks. He believed the chicks would ignore the dummy beak
altogether, but to his surprise, they pecked the red dot on this
cardboard beak just as much as they did the real one. Their attraction
to these red dots was clearly innate, not entirely learned. Tinbergen
then designed a series of beaks that changed the presentation of the dot
and studied the chicks&#39; reaction to them. Eventually, he designed a
beak that contained not one, but three unnaturally large and bright red
dots. When he presented it to them, the chicks turned frenetic, pecking
the beak as if it was the most joyous thing they were ever going to do.
Tinbergen studied other animals with similar innate attractions and
consistently found that he could exaggerate the characteristics of the
innately attractive to get the animals to react with an ardent desire
for it. He dubbed these &amp;quot;supernormal stimuli.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;centerimg&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;tinbergen.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;tinbergen.png&#34;
style=&#34;width: 50%;&#34; alt=&#34;Some of Tinbergen&amp;#39;s results.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some of Tinbergen&#39;s results.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this relevant? Well, the reactions of joyously desperate chicks
are quite adorable indeed... until you realize that there must be a
human equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-to-psychology&#34;&gt;... to psychology
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For millennia, we developed innate instincts and desires
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;#footnote-1&#34; &gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; that promoted our survival and reproduction. Salts,
fats, and sugars became attractive because they were rare but necessary
for survival. We developed a unique curiosity towards all kinds of
information because it all related to our real world and our survival in
it. Sex became stimulating because it promoted the passing of genes.
Even our attraction to that which is cute developed as a mechanism to
care for the young and vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in modern times, with the introduction of mass production and
growing consumer markets, companies began to realize, whether
consciously or unconsciously, that they too can easily appeal to our
innate desires to sell a product. The problem with this is that being
incontinent and excessively submitting to these impulses is a surefire
recipe for self-destruction. The modern diet is completely foreign to
what our ancestors ate, particularly because it is overloaded with
salts, fats, sugars, and all that which our bodies aren&#39;t prepared to
receive in large quantities. The advent of the digital age has allowed
us to overwhelm ourselves with vast amounts of information, most of
which will be completely unproductive and will ultimately subtract an
ungodly amount of time off of our lives, but will guarantee clicks,
views, and revenue nonetheless. And merely out of respect for myself,
and perhaps also out of concern for my sanity, I won&#39;t discuss the
abhorrent amount of time and money thrown into the deep, dark hole that
is &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; culture &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;#footnote-2&#34; &gt;\[2\]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, companies are not the main culprits. They only ever meet
demand. By desiring to have our innate desires satisfied at every
moment, &lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt; have created an environment that specializes and
continually becomes more efficient at doing so, and it won&#39;t hesitate
to push us to self-destruction if we so wish. If we instead wish to
avoid such a fate, then it is in our best interest we think twice about
following our desires. We shall here explore how mindlessly following
our impulses has fostered this dangerous environment and will continue
to strengthen it unless we stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-sell&#34;&gt;How to sell
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incontinence is an easy concept to understand. Just as an object in
motion remains in motion unless acted upon by another force, our
biological pull towards satisfying our innate desires will continue even
when it becomes counterproductive, unless we consciously attempt to stop
it. Traditional moral systems have historically been the force that
stopped this biological pull when it became self-destructive. Presently,
for reasons outside the scope of this article, these have greatly
diminished. The majority of people now have a vague understanding of or
even little interest in morality and distinguishing right from wrong,
and in this pop understanding of morality, incontinence falls
increasingly on the right side. If you&#39;re a company looking to sell a
product or a government looking to grow its economy, this is quite
convenient. Strong moral principles would simply sway demand against a
wide variety of consumptive habits. You can&#39;t sell sex to an abstainer
or alcohol to a teetotaler. Fortunately for you, however, your potential
consumers are already biologically primed towards fulfilling certain
innate desires as much as possible. You need only to offer them the
stimuli with which they can satisfy their craving, and then, with no
other act on your behalf, they will bite. Best of all, once they bite
it, few will hardly ever let go. Through habit their incontinence will
only reinforce itself, and they will return to you. The irony here is
that they will come to see their loyalty to you as an expression of
themselves, and some will even defend your business and your right to
operate in the &amp;quot;free&amp;quot; market, when in reality, their better judgment
overridden by their own incontinence, &lt;strong&gt;your own consumers have stopped
fully consenting to their consumption&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for you though, your products will almost certainly not be
the only fish in the sea. You will be fighting other companies for the
limited amount of time and money your potential customers have. To
ensure your continual survival, you must create products that
increasingly maximize customer satisfaction. Of course, you could try to
design a product that satisfies customers by actually providing a
benefit to them, undoubtedly some will, but if your goal still is to
maximize profits, then the sad reality is that in this world what
customers need does not outsell what customers want (or worse, what they
&lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; they need), and customers ardently want their innate desires
satisfied. Thus, anyone looking to acquire as much capital as possible
&lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; eventually have to betray its customers&#39; best interests and
push them towards incontinence. Now picture every company in the planet
trying to do so, and by mere Law of Least Effort, it becomes easier to
see why so many people today are slaves to their own impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;escape-the-supernormal&#34;&gt;Escape the supernormal
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What can be done about it? Frankly, I won&#39;t pretend I&#39;m too interested
in the large-scale transformation of our society. We all receive what we
dare to seek, and those who seek their own destruction will justly find
it. If, however, you belong to the few who seek to avoid it, then I can
at least offer some guidance on this less traveled path, taken from my
own personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our innate desires aren&#39;t inherently evil. Information, calories, and
even sexual gratification, though to a much lesser extent, are all part
of a good life. It is only when we corrupt or overuse these stimuli that
they become a force for evil in our lives. Engaging with stimuli this
way does feel pleasant, but, as you may already know, this will only
last a moment. The next dose of this stimulus will not be as pleasing,
and the more you try to chase its pleasure, the less it is within your
reach. What you may not know, however, is that as your brain adjusts
itself to the pleasure received from the stimulus, it becomes dependent
on it to function properly. In other words, the supernormal becomes
normal, the normal becomes tedious, and the challenging, where the
essence of life truly resides, becomes unbearable. Conversely, when one
rigorously abstains from corrupted and excessive pleasures, the normal
itself can become supernormally pleasing. Believe me, Reader, whatever
you seek out of life, it is not to be found in banal pleasures. Choose
to see the beauty in the normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Innate instincts, desires, cravings and
impulses are used interchangeably here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] These are only some of the negative
consequences of supernormal stimuli, and some of the bleaker ones at
that. See &lt;em&gt;Supernormal Stimuli&lt;/em&gt; below for more information on the true
harms of supernormal stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;see-also&#34;&gt;See also
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;atomic-habits-james-clear&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;, James Clear
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The book in which I first learned about supernormal stimuli. Note that
this book deals with the science behind behavior, not directly
supernormal stimuli. Still, I&#39;m sure those willing to break free from
incontinence will find this book to be of use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;supernormal-stimuli-how-primal-urges-overran-their-evolutionary-purpose-deirdre-barrett&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supernormal Stimuli: How Primal Urges Overran Their Evolutionary Purpose&lt;/em&gt;, Deirdre Barrett:
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;A book I stumbled upon while researching more on the topic. I cannot
recommend this enough if you wish to learn more about supernormal
stimuli themselves and their true potential for self-destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>WPA Supplicant - A Practical Guide</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/wpa_supplicant-a-practical-guide/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 17:13:36 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/wpa_supplicant-a-practical-guide/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/wpa_supplicant-a-practical-guide/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post WPA Supplicant - A Practical Guide" /&gt;&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;title&gt;WPA Supplicant - A practical guide&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;link rel=&#39;stylesheet&#39; type=&#39;text/css&#39; href=&#39;../style.css&#39;&gt;
&lt;meta charset=&#39;utf-8&#39;/&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita alrededor de 2022.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;main&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Index&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Preface&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Preface&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Installation&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Using the correct configuration file&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Using the correct configuration file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Editing the configuration file&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Editing the configuration file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Connecting to a network you know the credentials to&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Connecting to a network you know the credentials to&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Connecting to an enterprise network&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Connecting to an enterprise network&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Scanning for and connecting to open networks&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Scanning for and connecting to open networks&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Managing multiple networks&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Managing multiple networks&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Protecting your passphrases&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Protecting your passphrases&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Setting up the service&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Setting up the service&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#SystemD&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;SystemD&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Runit&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Runit&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#OpenRC&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;OpenRC&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#See also&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;See also&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Preface&#34;&gt;Preface&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This guide is meant to be a quick setup guide for &lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt;, designed primarily with Arch (&lt;i&gt;SystemD&lt;/i&gt;) and Artix (&lt;i&gt;runit&lt;/i&gt;) in mind. If you have no idea how to set up &lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt;, you should follow it thoroughly. If you have a very specific doubt, just skip to the section which will hopefully help you solve your problems; the sections are written independently from each other unless stated otherwise.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Note: Of course, installing these programs will require an active internet connection, which you probably do not have at this point. The installation should be done in the live ISO in which you also installed your operating system.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt; is sure to be found in your distribution&#39;s official repositories. You should also install &lt;i&gt;dhcpcd&lt;/i&gt; to get an IP address and complete the connection process. For default Arch-based, &lt;i&gt;SystemD&lt;/i&gt; distributions, a simple
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# pacman -S wpa_supplicant dhcpcd&lt;/code&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;should do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt; code { background-color: gray; color: blue; } &lt;/style&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, in distributions like Artix and Parabola, specific service scripts need to be installed for your init system. For example, using &lt;i&gt;runit&lt;/i&gt; as an init system for Artix, the following packages would also need to be installed:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# pacman -S wpa_supplicant-runit dhcpcd-runit&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;!--
&lt;p&gt;
And for &lt;i&gt;OpenRC&lt;/i&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# pacman -S wpa_supplicant-openrc dhcpcd-openrc&lt;/code&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Using the correct configuration file&#34;&gt;Using the correct configuration file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Note: WPA Supplicant is flexible enough to use any file as a configuration file, so none of these steps are technically necessary, but they are convention and will spare you a lot of confusion and file editting.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before connecting to the internet, you should know through which wireless interface you can do this with. Most often this will be &lt;code&gt;wlp2s0&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;wlan0&lt;/code&gt;, but you can quickly verify this by doing:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;$ ip a&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entries starting with &#34;wlp&#34; or &#34;wlan&#34; are the interfaces capable of wireless connection. You may have multiple of these if you have multiple wireless adapters, in which case you should choose one.&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configuration files are conventionally placed under &lt;code&gt;/etc/wpa_supplicant/&lt;/code&gt;, but their name changes according to the interface you wish to use. They follow the format &lt;code&gt;wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt;, so if your interface is &lt;code&gt;wlan0&lt;/code&gt;, your complete file path would be &lt;code&gt;/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-wlan0.conf&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Editing the configuration file&#34;&gt;Editing the configuration file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Connecting to a network you know the credentials to&#34;&gt;Connecting to a network you know the credentials to&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Adding a standard WPA2 network is most commonly done through &lt;i&gt;wpa_passphrase&lt;/i&gt;. This program takes in two simple arguments: the network&#39;s SSID (name) and its passphrase. Take a look at this intuitive example:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;$ wpa_passphrase MyNetwork password123&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
network={
ssid=&#34;MyNetwork&#34;
#psk=&#34;password123&#34;
psk=1f1503df6a9182b5936a027973a426df3954bb0ff5d4add55753fe37b02a55f1
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This output can then be redirected into your configuration file in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;# wpa_passphrase MyNetwork password123 &gt;&gt; /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or if you prefer to use &lt;i&gt;sudo&lt;/i&gt; over a root shell:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;$ wpa_passphrase MyNetwork password123 | sudo tee -a /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#Protecting your passphrases&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Protecting your passphrases&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
presents more options for those concerned with security, but as a bare minimum manually deleting the plaintext versions of your passphrases should do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point restarting the service will load in the edited configuration file and, if the credentials are valid, will connect you to the internet. If you do not know how to do this, read &lt;a href=&#34;#Setting up the service&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Setting up the service&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Connecting to an enterprise network&#34;&gt;Connecting to an enterprise network&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enterprise networks do not have a program like &lt;i&gt;wpa_passphrase&lt;/i&gt; to fill in entries, but they follow a similar format. Still, if you need to connect to a network of this kind, you will have to manually add the entry. These networks utilize the following format:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
network={
ssid=&#34;AnEnterpriseNetwork&#34;
key_mgmt=WPA-EAP
eap=PEAP
identity=&#34;user_name&#34;
password=&#34;user_password&#34;
phase2=&#34;autheap=MSCHAPV2&#34;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Considering that you are utilizing a plain-text password and are unable to get around it, it is advisable that you follow the strictest protocols dictated in &lt;a href=&#34;#Protecting your passphrases&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;Protecting your passphrases&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Scanning for and connecting to open networks&#34;&gt;Scanning for and connecting to open networks&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable network scanning, the following line must be added in the configuration file, preferably at the beginning: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;ctrl_interface=/run/wpa_supplicant&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To actually scan for networks, a separate program must be used, in a similar vein to &lt;i&gt;wpa_passphrase&lt;/i&gt;. This program is &lt;i&gt;wpa_cli&lt;/i&gt;, and does require root privileges. The program will start interactively with a simple:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;# wpa_cli&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You should be greeted by some text and a simple &lt;code&gt;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, indicating you are in interactive mode. To begin a scan, all that is necessary is to execute the command:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&gt; scan&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
which, after some time, should yield the output:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&gt; scan
OK
&lt;3&gt;CTRL-EVENT-SCAN-STARTED
&lt;3&gt;CTRL-EVENT-SCAN-RESULTS
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
point at which you can see the scan&#39;s results by doing:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&gt; scan_results&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Networks detected withing your range should be presented, and from them, open networks should look something like the following (notice the lack of flags when compared to a normal entry):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&gt; scan_results
bssid / frequency / signal level / flags / ssid
XX:XX:XX:XX:XX:XX   XXXX-XX     [WPA2-PSK-CCMP][WPS][ESS]       AClosedAndProtectedNetwork
XX:XX:XX:XX:XX:XX   XXXX-XX     [ESS]       AnOpenAndInsecureNetwork
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You should know that there is a way to interactively connect to networks and save their credentials (or lack thereof) to the configuration file automatically, but frankly since I only ever use &lt;i&gt;wpa_cli&lt;/i&gt; to connect to open networks I choose to just manually add the short entry for this kind of network, like so:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
network={
   ssid=&#34;AnOpenAndInsecureNetwork&#34;
   key_mgmt=NONE
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Managing multiple networks&#34;&gt;Managing multiple networks&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes multiple networks are available in the same area, in which case you might prefer using one over the other. This can be easily done through the use of prioritization. In &lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt;&#39;s configuration file, this is done with the &lt;code&gt;priority&lt;/code&gt; parameter inside the network entries. The networks with the highest priority will actually be those with the highest value, so the highest priority a network can have is 999.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To illustrate its usage, all previous examples are gathered here, organized with the home network always having the highest priority, the enterprise network having the second highest and the open network having the lowest priority possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
ctrl_interface=/run/wpa_supplicant
&lt;p&gt;# Home network
network={
ssid=&amp;ldquo;MyNetwork&amp;rdquo;
psk=1f1503df6a9182b5936a027973a426df3954bb0ff5d4add55753fe37b02a55f1
priority=999
}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;# Enterprise network
network={
ssid=&amp;ldquo;AnEnterpriseNetwork&amp;rdquo;
key_mgmt=WPA-EAP
eap=PEAP
identity=&amp;ldquo;user_name&amp;rdquo;
password=&amp;ldquo;user_password&amp;rdquo;
phase2=&amp;ldquo;autheap=MSCHAPV2&amp;rdquo;
priority=998
}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;# Open network
network={
ssid=&amp;ldquo;AnOpenAndInsecureNetwork&amp;rdquo;
key_mgmt=NONE
priority=-999
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Protecting your passphrases&#34;&gt;Protecting your passphrases&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Your configuration file will hold the credentials to multiple networks, and considering how much sensitive information can go through these, it is important you protect them.
&lt;/p&gt;
The most basic form of protection would be to delete plaintext password from your configuration file, since they are already made redundant by the ciphered passphrases. This step already goes a long way in protecting your credentials, and if you do not share your computer with other people, is as far as you would have to go. Anything else is just for reinforcement&#39;s sake.
&lt;p&gt;
If you wish to keep your plaintext passphrases and still want to prevent other users from seeing them, you can change your configuration file&#39;s permissions so that only privileged users can see them. Assuming that the file and directory already belong to root (which they will if you haven not explicitly changed it), all you need to do is to change permissions on the file so that other users do not have read or execute permissions. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;# chmod 600 /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt;.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, if you insist on protecting your passphrases, you should also consider clearing your shell&#39;s history file so that it is not readable there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Setting up the service&#34;&gt;Setting up the service&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Starting the &lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt; service is highly dependent on the init system you are running. This particular guide covers enabling the services under &lt;i&gt;SystemD&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;runit&lt;/i&gt;, but enabling it under other init systems should not be too dissimilar.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;SystemD&#34;&gt;SystemD&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have organized your configuration file as detailed in the previous section, enabling the service should be as simple as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# systemctl enable dhcpcd wpa_supplicant@&lt;i&gt;[interface]&lt;/i&gt; --now&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;Runit&#34;&gt;Runit&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unlike with &lt;i&gt;SystemD&lt;/i&gt;, you do not want to just initialize the service. You have to first explicitly configure the script to point to the configuration file and interface you wish to use. This script is located in &lt;code&gt;/etc/runit/sv/wpa_supplicant/run&lt;/code&gt;. The &#34;official&#34; way of doing this is by creating a &lt;code&gt;conf&lt;/code&gt; file in the same directory and populating with the variables &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; calls for, like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/runit/sv/wpa_supplicant/conf&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
#!/bin/sh
CONF_FILE=/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-wlp2s0.conf
WPA_INTERFACE=wlp2s0
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I find this a bit too redundant, which is why I prefer to edit the &lt;i&gt;run&lt;/i&gt; file directly, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/runit/sv/wpa_supplicant/run&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
#!/bin/sh
#[ -r ./conf ] &amp;&amp; . ./conf
exec 2&gt;&amp;1
#exec wpa_supplicant -c ${CONF_FILE:=/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf} -i ${WPA_INTERFACE:=wlan0} ${OPTS:=-s}
exec wpa_supplicant -c /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-wlp2s0.conf -i wlp2s0 ${OPTS:=-s}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Either way will work just fine. Now you can proceed to actually enabling the services, which in &lt;i&gt;runit&lt;/i&gt; is done by doing:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# ln -s /etc/runit/sv/dhcpcd /run/runit/dhcpcd&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# ln -s /etc/runit/sv/wpa_supplicant /run/runit/wpa_supplicant&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, to start the services:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;# sv start dhcpcd wpa_supplicant&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;OpenRC&#34;&gt;OpenRC&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Edit /etc/init.d/wpa_supplicant to include the desired interface and configuration file.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-bottom: 0; border-bottom:none; padding-bottom:0.8em;&#34;&gt;/etc/init.d/wpa_supplicant&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre style=&#34;margin-top: 0; border-top-style:dashed; padding-top: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;
#!/usr/bin/openrc-run
# Copyright (c) 2009 Roy Marples &lt;roy@marples.name&gt;
# All rights reserved. Released under the 2-clause BSD license.
&lt;p&gt;command=/usr/bin/wpa_supplicant
: ${wpa_supplicant_conf:=/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf}
wpa_supplicant_if=${wpa_supplicant_if:+-i}$wpa_supplicant_if
#command_args=&amp;quot;$wpa_supplicant_args -B -c$wpa_supplicant_conf $wpa_supplicant_if&amp;quot;
command_args=&amp;quot;$wpa_supplicant_args -B -c/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant-wlan0.conf wlan0&amp;quot;
name=&amp;ldquo;WPA Supplicant Daemon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now just enable the service:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;code-commands&#34;&gt;
# rc-update add dhcpcd default
# rc-update add wpa_supplicant default&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;See also&#34;&gt;See also&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Wpa_supplicant&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt; on the Arch Wiki: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
Excellent resource if you want to go more in-depth and plan to do something more complicated.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linux.die.net/man/8/wpa_supplicant&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;wpa_supplicant(8):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
Manual page for &lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linux.die.net/man/5/wpa_supplicant.conf&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;wpa_supplicant.conf(5):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
Manual page for &lt;i&gt;wpa_supplicant&lt;/i&gt;&#39;s configuration file.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linux.die.net/man/8/wpa_passphrase&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;toctext&#34;&gt;wpa_passphrase(8):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
Manual page for &lt;i&gt;wpa_passphrase&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/main&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Removing the Supervisor Password on a Thinkpad</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/removing-the-supervisor-password-on-a-thinkpad/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 12:01:12 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/removing-the-supervisor-password-on-a-thinkpad/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCLAIMER: I do not condone illegally tampering with another person&amp;rsquo;s device. This guide was created with the intention of helping those who have acquired an old, used laptop that is only not perfectly functional because of this password. Also, I take NO RESPONSIBILITY for any harm done to your motherboard. It should go without saying that you should be careful when doing this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIOS-locked laptops are often sold incredibly cheap because your average layman thinks that they are bricked and worthless. In reality, removing the BIOS passwords is a piece of cake. This guide will only be covering the older method of removing BIOS passwords that does not work on more modern hardware. This guide is also written with Thinkpads in mind (the most modern Thinkpads this can be done being the **30 series machines, from 2012), but in theory this should work for other laptops as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;types-of-passwords&#34;&gt;Types of passwords
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, Thinkpads can have three kinds of passwords in their BIOS: the Hard Disk Password (HDP), the Power-On Password (POP) and the Supervisor Password (SVP). The HDP is rarely a problem since the old computer you bought probably didn&amp;rsquo;t even come with the hard-drive protected by that password. The POP is the easiest password to clear, and the SVP is the most common BIOS password found on Thinkpads. The reset method for the SVP can, in theory, be used as the end-all be-all to clear all passwords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;finding-the-eeprom&#34;&gt;Finding the EEPROM
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EEPROM is the chip which needs to be tampered with in order to successfully reset the SVP. This chip can be found in all sorts of weird places across different kinds of motherboards. The X200, the machine I actually did this with, has the chip conveniently placed under the palm rest, meaning that unscrewing the keyboard and the palm rest is all you need to do to access it. For other Thinkpads though, it&amp;rsquo;s not nearly as easy or convenient. On the W series for example, &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6AhQda_8Vy0&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;it&amp;rsquo;s almost a complete disassembly&lt;/a&gt;. You also need to locate two particular pins on the EEPROM, namely the SCL and SDA pins. &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.ja.axxs.net/eeprom_location.htm&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find the EEPROM and pin locations, as well as links to the hardware manuals to disassemble your machine. (Note that the website is for a piece of hardware you can buy to tinker with the EEPROM, but all we care about is the EEPROM&amp;rsquo;s location and pin layout.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-were-actually-doing&#34;&gt;What we&amp;rsquo;re actually doing
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is mere speculation on my behalf, as truth be told I&amp;rsquo;m not exactly sure why this works, I just know it does, but if you understand the EEPROM this way then you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to remove the password with no problem. What we&amp;rsquo;re going to do is short out the SCL and SDA pins shortly after booting. This will send the BIOS into an abnormal state in which it can&amp;rsquo;t properly read from or write to the motherboard, meaning it only loads the default, &amp;ldquo;passwordless&amp;rdquo; BIOS. &lt;strong&gt;The BIOS menu will remain in this abnormal state for as long as you keep the pins shorted&lt;/strong&gt;, which is why once you&amp;rsquo;re promted to enter the new supervisor password, &lt;strong&gt;you must let go of the pins to&lt;/strong&gt; successfully write the new password to the motherboard. (Actually, you may even be able to let go of the pins once you&amp;rsquo;re in the menu. For the sake of safety I just held the pins until I was prompted for the new password.) &lt;strong&gt;Keeping the pins shorted the entire time will not work.&lt;/strong&gt; Trust me. I tried, many, many, many times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-steps&#34;&gt;The steps
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that you know where the EEPROM is, how it works and where its SCL and SDA pins are, you can proceed to actually removing the password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unplug the laptop and disconnect the battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disassemble the laptop and reach the EEPROM. Again, the EEPROM&amp;rsquo;s location (and thus how much you need to disassemble) depends on your Thinkpad model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plug the computer to power. If it didn&amp;rsquo;t already, turn it on. Make sure you have a screwdriver nearby though, because from here on out you&amp;rsquo;ll need to be quick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as the Thinkpad logo appears, short the pins and begin spamming F1 to get to the BIOS menu. You short the pins by making sure their metal is in contact with the metal tip of your screwdriver. If you successfully shorted the pins, then the computer should report various errors. They&amp;rsquo;re not always the same, but the many times I tried I remember seeing an error related to the CMOS time followed by a RAID or ES-something error and finally, the most important one, a security error. If you did not see these or you reach the BIOS in user mode (the one that requires and empty password and cannot change many items), then you must try again. Keep a steady hand and make sure the screwdriver is making contact with both pins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the pins shorted, navigate to Security &amp;gt; Password &amp;gt; Supervisor Password. Hit Enter to receive the prompt to change it. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if you need to keep the pins shorted for this long, you&amp;rsquo;re probably able to let go of them as soon as you reach the menu, but I held them up to this point so I can&amp;rsquo;t verify this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let go of the pins, then enter a blank password. That should disable the SVP. Hit F10 to save and exit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, the SVP is now disabled. But you&amp;rsquo;ll have to manually set the CMOS time if that reset itself, else you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to boot. You may also wish to change other values in the BIOS menu, like the Fn/Ctrl swap or the Thinkpad&amp;rsquo;s beeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ps-should-i-do-this-even-if-i-want-to-install-libreboot&#34;&gt;P.S. Should I do this even if I want to install Libreboot?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you find a Thinkpad with a locked BIOS and wish to install Libreboot, then you could technically skip this altogether. Libreboot will not have any problems overwriting the default BIOS. However, if you ever need the regular BIOS again, then even if you saved a copy it&amp;rsquo;ll still be locked. Also, the Libreboot documentation for the X200 and other Thinkpads recommends &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://libreboot.org/docs/install/#ec-update-on-i945-x60-t60-and-gm45-x200-x301-t400-t500-r400-w500-r500&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;updating the EC firmware on your computer&lt;/a&gt; before flashing, since it can&amp;rsquo;t be done afterwards. All-in-all I&amp;rsquo;d say if you&amp;rsquo;re already going to open up the laptop to install Libreboot on it then this process is going to be easy enough for you and could save you from some future headaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>El salón de fama de Dios</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/el-salon-de-fama-de-dios/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 09:58:18 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/el-salon-de-fama-de-dios/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lo que procede es mi intento de traducir al español uno de mis poemas contemporáneos favoritos, &lt;em&gt;God&amp;rsquo;s Hall of Fame&lt;/em&gt;, tradicionalmente adjudicado a Alf Hutchinson, mantentiendo una métrica decasílaba constante y sin rima. Quizá para la próxima intente traducir la versión extendida, narrada por Jim Caviezel en &lt;em&gt;The Sound of Freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#39;text-align: center;&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tu nombre podría estar ausente&lt;br&gt;
del salón de fama de este mundo.&lt;br&gt;
Podrías ser tan desconocido,&lt;br&gt;
pocos tu nombre conocerán.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La fama y la fortuna te eluden,&lt;br&gt;
pues sólo a unos pocos se conceden,&lt;br&gt;
Pero si al Señor amas y sirves,&lt;br&gt;
buenas noticias hay para ti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este salón de fama perdura&lt;br&gt;
sólo mientras el mundo perdure,&lt;br&gt;
pero considera que eterno es&lt;br&gt;
el salón de la fama de Dios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tu nombre tener inscrito arriba&lt;br&gt;
enormemente más grandioso es&lt;br&gt;
que todos los salones del mundo&lt;br&gt;
y cada estrella hecha por el hombre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pronto olvida la gente del mundo&lt;br&gt;
a aquellos héroes del pasado.&lt;br&gt;
Ellos aplauden hasta que caes,&lt;br&gt;
y solamente eso es lo que duras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pero no el Señor, pues nunca olvida,&lt;br&gt;
y verás que en Su salón de fama,&lt;br&gt;
por el hecho de creer en Su Hijo,&lt;br&gt;
inscrito tu nombre encontrarás.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Te digo amigo, no cambiaría&lt;br&gt;
mi nombre, por pequeño que sea,&lt;br&gt;
inscrito aun pasando las estrellas&lt;br&gt;
en ese alto salón celestial&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por cada nombre famoso aquí,&lt;br&gt;
o la gloria que juntos comparten.&lt;br&gt;
Prefiero un donnadie ser aquí&lt;br&gt;
¡y mi nombre ahí arriba encontrar!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Película sobrevalorada por cierto, pero al menos el poema es bueno.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Instalación de Arch Linux</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/instalacion-de-arch-linux/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 19:53:49 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/instalacion-de-arch-linux/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/instalacion-de-arch-linux/arch-install.png" alt="Featured image of post Instalación de Arch Linux" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A continuación presento una lista de los comandos utilizados en &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://youtu.be/rDiilGzZNsE&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;mi video guía de instalación de Arch Linux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;iso-si-es-que-se-está-instalando-desde-una-instalación-pre-existente-de-linux&#34;&gt;ISO (si es que se está instalando desde una instalación pre-existente de Linux)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;sudo dd if=arch-2024-12-04.iso of=/dev/sdb
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nótese que &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; significa &amp;ldquo;input file&amp;rdquo;, la cual es el ISO descargado, mientras que &lt;code&gt;of&lt;/code&gt; es &amp;ldquo;output file&amp;rdquo; y debe ser el dispositivo USB al cual se le va a quemar el ISO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;teclado-disponibles-en-usrsharekbdkeymaps&#34;&gt;TECLADO (disponibles en /usr/share/kbd/keymaps)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-gdscript3&#34; data-lang=&#34;gdscript3&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;loadkeys&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;la&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;latin1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;verificar-modo-de-arranque-gptuefi-v-mbr&#34;&gt;VERIFICAR MODO DE ARRANQUE (GPT/UEFI v MBR)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;cat /sys/firmware/efi/fw_platform_size
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;conectarse-a-internet-recomendable-conectarse-por-ethernet&#34;&gt;CONECTARSE A INTERNET (recomendable conectarse por ethernet)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;ping danielml.mx # si se obtiene información, se está conectado a Internet
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;ip a # para obtener nombre de la estación
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;iwctl --passphrase passphrase station name connect SSID
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;crear-las-particiones&#34;&gt;CREAR LAS PARTICIONES
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;cgdisk /dev/sdX
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hacer partición boot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hacer partición swap (código 8200)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hacer partición root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;formatear-las-particiones&#34;&gt;FORMATEAR LAS PARTICIONES
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mkfs.vfat [boot]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mkfs.ext4 [/]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mkswap /dev/swap_partition
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;montar-las-particiones&#34;&gt;MONTAR LAS PARTICIONES
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;cd /mnt
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mount /dev/sdXN /mnt
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mkdir boot
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mount /dev/sdXN boot/
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;seleccionar-mirrors-opcional-recomendado&#34;&gt;SELECCIONAR MIRRORS (opcional, recomendado)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;vi /etc/pacman.d/mirrorlist
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mover mirrors más cercanos geográficamente a la cima del archivo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;instalación-de-paquetes-base&#34;&gt;INSTALACIÓN DE PAQUETES BASE
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;pacstrap /mnt base base-devel linux linux-firmware wpa_supplicant dhcpcd 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;generar-tabla-de-fs-file-system-table&#34;&gt;GENERAR TABLA DE FS (FILE SYSTEM TABLE)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;si-estás-haciendo-dual-boot-con-windows&#34;&gt;SI ESTÁS HACIENDO DUAL BOOT CON WINDOWS
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mkdir boot/efi
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mount /dev/sda1 boot/efi
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;genfstab -U /mnt / &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /mnt/etc/fstab
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;entrar-al-sistema&#34;&gt;ENTRAR AL SISTEMA
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;arch-chroot /mnt
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;generar-locales&#34;&gt;GENERAR LOCALES
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;nvim /etc/locale.gen   # descomentar los locales preferidos (ej. en_US.UTF8
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;locale-gen
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;nvim /etc/locale.conf  # escribir LANG=[locale preferido] (ej. LANG=en_US.UTF8)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;elegir-zona-de-tiempo&#34;&gt;ELEGIR ZONA DE TIEMPO
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;ln -sf /usr/share/zoneinfo/Region/City /etc/localtime
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;hwclock --systohc
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;elegir-formato-de-teclado&#34;&gt;ELEGIR FORMATO DE TECLADO
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;nvim /etc/vconsole.conf     # escribir KEYMAP=[teclado preferido] (ej.KEYMAP=la-latin1)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;crear-hostname&#34;&gt;CREAR HOSTNAME
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;nvim /etc/hostname      # escribir nombre de máquina de tu elección
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;establecer-hosts&#34;&gt;ESTABLECER HOSTS
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;nvim /etc/hosts     # escribir lo siguiente, reemplazando [hostname] con el nombre de máquina seleccionado
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;# 127.0.0.1	localhost
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;# ::1		localhost
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;# 127.0.1.1	[hostname].locadomain	[hostname]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;compilar-mkinitcpio&#34;&gt;COMPILAR MKINITCPIO
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;mkinitpcio -p linux
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;instalar-bootloader&#34;&gt;INSTALAR BOOTLOADER
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;pacman -S grub os-prober efibootmgr
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;si-estás-haciendo-dual-boot-con-windows-1&#34;&gt;SI ESTÁS HACIENDO DUAL BOOT CON WINDOWS
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;nvim /etc/default/grub      # descomentar GRUB_DISABLE_OS_PROBER=false
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-gdscript3&#34; data-lang=&#34;gdscript3&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;grub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x86_64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;efi&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;efi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;directory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;boot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;efi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;bootloader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;GRUB&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;grub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;mkconfig&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;o&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;boot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;grub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;grub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;cfg&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;crear-contraseña&#34;&gt;CREAR CONTRASEÑA
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-fallback&#34; data-lang=&#34;fallback&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;passwd
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Mi biblioteca personal</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 21:02:59 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post Mi biblioteca personal" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dicen que puedes aprender mucho de un hombre en base a los libros que tiene en su estante. Presento aquí entonces, en ningún orden en particular, una lista casi exhaustiva de los libros que tengo físicamente. Dicho esto, no porque los tenga significa que los haya leído, y no porque un libro no aparezca aquí significa que no lo haya leído, pues francamente la mayoría de los libros los he pirateado digitalmente. Aun así, muchos de estos libros tienen un lugar especial en mi corazón, especialmente aquellos resaltados.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;biblia-dios-habla-hoy-con-deuterocanónicos&#34;&gt;Biblia &amp;ldquo;Dios Habla Hoy&amp;rdquo; (con Deuterocanónicos)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;steve-jobs---karen-blumenthal&#34;&gt;Steve Jobs - Karen Blumenthal
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;fahrenheit-451---ray-bradbury&#34;&gt;Fahrenheit 451 - Ray Bradbury
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-win-friends--influence-people---dale-carnegie&#34;&gt;How to Win Friends &amp;amp; Influence People - Dale Carnegie
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;el-alquimista---paulo-coelho&#34;&gt;El Alquimista - Paulo Coelho
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;manual-del-guerrero-de-la-luz---paulo-coelho&#34;&gt;Manual del guerrero de la luz - Paulo Coelho
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;la-era-del-vacío---gilles-lipovetsky&#34;&gt;La era del vacío - Gilles Lipovetsky
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-six-pillars-of-self-esteem---nathaniel-branden&#34;&gt;The Six Pillars of Self-Esteem - Nathaniel Branden
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;inferno---dante-alighieri-traducción-de-john-ciardi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inferno - Dante Alighieri (traducción de John Ciardi)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;purgatorio---dante-alighieri-traducción-de-john-ciardi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purgatorio - Dante Alighieri (traducción de John Ciardi)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;paradiso---dante-alighieri-traducción-de-john-ciardi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paradiso - Dante Alighieri (traducción de John Ciardi)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/comedia-600.png&#34;
	width=&#34;600&#34;
	height=&#34;306&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/comedia-600_hu_d6dd17879352d25f.png 480w, https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/comedia-600_hu_4403ece0478348ca.png 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;La Divina Commedia&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;196&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;470px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;la-rebelión-de-las-masas---josé-ortega-y-gasset&#34;&gt;La rebelión de las masas - José Ortega y Gasset
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;confesiones---san-agustín&#34;&gt;Confesiones - San Agustín
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;la-inteligencia-emocional---daniel-goleman&#34;&gt;La inteligencia emocional - Daniel Goleman
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;atomic-habits---james-clear&#34;&gt;Atomic Habits - James Clear
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;los-hermanos-karamazov-1-y-2---fyodor-mikhaylovich-dostoyevskiy&#34;&gt;Los hermanos Karamazov (1 y 2) - Fyodor Mikhaylovich Dostoyevskiy
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;king-warrior-magician-lover-rediscovering-the-archetype-of-the-mature-masculine---robert-moore--douglas-gillette&#34;&gt;King Warrior Magician Lover: Rediscovering the Archetype of the Mature Masculine - Robert Moore &amp;amp; Douglas Gillette
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;iron-john---robert-bly&#34;&gt;Iron John - Robert Bly
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;manhood-in-the-making-cultural-concepts-of-masculinity---david-d-gilmore&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manhood in the Making: Cultural Concepts of Masculinity - David D. Gilmore&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/manhood-400.png&#34;
	width=&#34;400&#34;
	height=&#34;603&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/manhood-400_hu_83b3a3df57f2e1e8.png 480w, https://danielml.mx/posts/mi-biblioteca-personal/manhood-400_hu_931d2493e5dded4f.png 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;66&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;159px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;discurso-del-método-y-meditaciones-metafísicas---rené-descartes&#34;&gt;Discurso del método y Meditaciones metafísicas - René Descartes
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sobre-el-inconveniente-de-tener-muchos-amigos-y-otros-ensayos---plutarco&#34;&gt;Sobre el inconveniente de tener muchos amigos (y otros ensayos) - Plutarco
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;moral-courage---rushworth-m-kidder&#34;&gt;Moral Courage - Rushworth M. Kidder
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;nadie-supo-nada-la-verdadera-historia-del-asesinato-de-eugenio-garza-sada---jorge-fernández-menéndez&#34;&gt;Nadie supo nada: La verdadera historia del asesinato de Eugenio Garza Sada - Jorge Fernández Menéndez
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;tu-vida-tu-mejor-negocio---salvador-alva&#34;&gt;Tu vida: tu mejor negocio - Salvador Alva
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-eugenio-garza-sada---gabriela-recio-cavazos&#34;&gt;Don Eugenio Garza Sada - Gabriela Recio Cavazos
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;la-raza-cósmica---josé-vasconcelos&#34;&gt;La raza cósmica - José Vasconcelos
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;breve-historia-de-méxico---josé-vasconcelos&#34;&gt;Breve historia de México - José Vasconcelos
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-myths-of-mexico-and-perú---lewis-spence&#34;&gt;The Myths of Mexico and Perú - Lewis Spence
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;life-at-the-bottom-the-worldview-that-makes-the-underclass---theodore-dalrymple&#34;&gt;Life at the Bottom: The Worldview that Makes the Underclass - Theodore Dalrymple
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;flow-the-psychology-of-optimal-experience---mihaly-csikszentmihalyi&#34;&gt;Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience - Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sapiens-de-animales-a-dioses---yuval-noah-harari&#34;&gt;Sapiens: De animales a dioses - Yuval Noah Harari
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;el-lobo-estepario---herman-hesse&#34;&gt;El lobo estepario - Herman Hesse
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;youcat-latinoamérica&#34;&gt;YOUCAT Latinoamérica
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;imitación-de-cristo---tomás-de-kempis&#34;&gt;Imitación de Cristo - Tomás de Kempis
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;dios-sí-iglesia-no-respuestas-fáciles-a-preguntas-difíciles-para-jóvenes---julio-muñoz-lópez-de-carrizosa-lc&#34;&gt;Dios sí. Iglesia no. Respuestas fáciles a preguntas difíciles para jóvenes - Julio Muñoz López de Carrizosa, LC
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;el-príncipe---nicolás-maquiavelo&#34;&gt;El príncipe - Nicolás Maquiavelo
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1984---george-orwell&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1984 - George Orwell&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-art-of-war---sun-tzu&#34;&gt;The Art of War - Sun Tzu
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-black-swan-the-impact-of-the-highly-improbable---nassim-nicholas-taleb&#34;&gt;The Black Swan: The Impact of the Highly Improbable - Nassim Nicholas Taleb
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;antifragile-things-that-gain-from-disorder---nassim-nicholas-taleb&#34;&gt;Antifragile: Things That Gain From Disorder - Nassim Nicholas Taleb
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;skin-in-the-game-hidden-asymmetries-in-daily-life---nassim-nicholas-taleb&#34;&gt;Skin in the Game: Hidden Asymmetries in Daily Life - Nassim Nicholas Taleb
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;la-biblia-de-jerusalén---great-adventure-bible&#34;&gt;La Biblia de Jerusalén - Great Adventure Bible
&lt;/h3&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Sobre mí</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/about/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 17:23:24 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/about/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;quién-soy&#34;&gt;¿Quién soy?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soy Daniel Muñoz Lozano, tengo 22 años y actualmente estudio la doble titulación de Economía y Derecho en el Tecnológico de Monterrey. Me considero una persona valiente y curiosa, intentando ser humilde y magnánimo. Mi religión católica guía todas mis decisiones y es un componente esencial de mi identidad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mis-intereses&#34;&gt;Mis intereses
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Videografía, política, economía, software libre, entrenamiento canino, gimnasio, catolicismo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mis-obras-favoritas&#34;&gt;Mis obras favoritas
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/strong&gt; - Dante Alighieri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Models: Attract Women Through Honesty&lt;/strong&gt; - Mark Manson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industrial Society and Its Future&lt;/strong&gt; - Theodore Kaczynski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skin in the Game: Hidden Asymmetries in Daily Life&lt;/strong&gt; - Nassim Nicholas Taleb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manhood in the Making: Cultural Concepts of Masculinity&lt;/strong&gt; - David D. Gilmore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boys Adrift: The Five Factors Driving the Growing Epidemic of Unmotivated Boys and Underachieving Young Men&lt;/strong&gt; - Leonard Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;atribuciones-créditos-y-redistribución&#34;&gt;Atribuciones, créditos y redistribución
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Este sitio fue creado con &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; y el tema &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/CaiJimmy/hugo-theme-stack&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Stack&lt;/a&gt; de &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://jimmycai.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Jimmy&lt;/a&gt;. Además, todo el contenido de este sitio está protegido bajo la licencia CC BY-NC-ND 4.0, lo cual a grandes rasgos significa que se puede redistribuir siempre y cuando se proporcione crédito al autor, no se modifique lo dicho y se redistribuya sin fines comerciales. Por otro lado, el &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/danielml-mx/danielml.mx&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;código de este sitio web&lt;/a&gt; se puede redistribuir bajo los términos de la GPLv3 (la única licencia de código buena).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Entradas</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/archives/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/archives/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Buscar</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/search/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/search/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Ligas</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/links/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/links/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
