<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Filosofía 🤔 on Daniel Muñoz Lozano</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/tags/filosof%C3%ADa-/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Filosofía 🤔 on Daniel Muñoz Lozano</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:12:11 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://danielml.mx/tags/filosof%C3%ADa-/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>1984, George Orwell - Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/1984-orwell-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:12:11 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/1984-orwell-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/1984-orwell-thoughts/MassSurveillance.jpg" alt="Featured image of post 1984, George Orwell - Thoughts" /&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales de 2021.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Sanity is not statistical.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;George Orwell, &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; even need an introduction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year is 1984. Three totalitarian super-states have divided the world
among themselves. Oceania, the Western super-state, includes the
war-torn city of London, home to Winston Smith. As a member of the
Ministry of Truth, he alters historical records to coincide with
whatever the Party desires. To the outside world, he is just another
obedient pawn. On the inside, however, Winston doubts. In a society
omnipresent with telescreens and the mighty Big Brother, Winston knows
he&#39;s doomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A classic I have waited far too long to read, &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; does not
disappoint. Though it presents an all-around outstanding plot, it is the
real-life context behind the novel which I find more fascinating. The
hopelessness of the war and post-war eras is clearly presented in the
general unwillingness of the characters to think deeply about complex
matters, but that does not mean Orwell meant for &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; to be a direct
prediction of where this trajectory would lead us, much less another
cautionary tale on communism, contrary to what many took it for. After
all, Orwell himself, as a democratic socialist, was pretty left-leaning.
In reality, while the novel was in some senses inspired by the
atrocities of Stalin, its primary political focus is to discuss the
phenomenon of power. Orwell knew that what once was valid criticism
against the inequalities and atrocities of capitalism had become a cheap
tactic for politicians to prey on the misery and desperation of the
masses so as to gain popularity and, ultimately, power. Hitler did it,
Stalin did it, and Oceania does it. &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; is merely an exaggeration of
this form of manipulation applied on a global scale and projected into
the future, meant to relate Orwell&#39;s concerns to the world. That, at
least in part, is a timeless message, and relates a concern we should
still be on the lookout for even today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I can&#39;t really talk about my favorite part of the novel
without spoiling the plot, but once you get to this part, you&#39;ll
realize this too: the plot doesn&#39;t even really matter. Even now, as
most people know at least the general details of the story of &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;
perhaps without having read it, the book is still worth a read. The real
horror of &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; is found in the way Orwell toys with your perception of
the inner machinations of the Party. The fact that he doesn&#39;t spend too
much time presenting the Party actually works in favor of &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;, as the
lack of information preys on the reader&#39;s fears and ideas about how
ruthlessly totalitarian a government would have to be to reach the level
of power the Party has reached. Is the Party fallible? We may never
determine it with certainty, but a good place to start would be the
first few pages of the novel, if you know what I mean. &lt;em&gt;Al chile ni yo me acuerdo por qué jajajaj.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I can talk about, at least generally, is Winston Smith. The story
is told mostly through his own thoughts, not dialogue, which, again,
actually works in favor of the novel. The narrative style feels
remarkably intimate and personal, completely removed from the orthodoxy
of his environment and, at times, even of his own actions. I think we
can all relate to a moment in our lives in which we took a hard look at
a particular well-accepted attitude of our society, perhaps a
crowd-pleasing fad or an out-of-date tradition, and said &amp;quot;This isn&#39;t
right,&amp;quot; but decided that looking like the odd one out would be too much
of a hassle, so we just quietly acted as would be expected from us.
Winston&#39;s life is this moment constantly in repeat, his actions
betraying his own thoughts over and over again for the sake of safety.
This is most apparent in his conversation with his friend Syme, who
Winston recognizes is smarter than the rest and, though he never finds
direct evidence, knows about Winston&#39;s heterodox thoughts. It creates a
tension that makes you wonder whether or not Winston will ever become
rebellious enough to falter when dissimulating, thus making his facade
visible to the rest, including the dreaded Thought Police, a situation
perhaps allegorical to our ever more close-minded world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; has proved to be timelessly relevant. You may find the lying
&amp;quot;Ministry of Truth&amp;quot; and the torturous &amp;quot;Ministry of Love&amp;quot; silly, but
I know you know about the vulnerabilities kept secret by the &amp;quot;National
Security Agency&amp;quot; and the suppression at Tiananmen at the hands of the
&amp;quot;People&#39;s Liberation Army.&amp;quot; There have always been and perhaps will
always be people who will take us all for fools and try to use us to
gain and remain in power. We won&#39;t prevent their success by keeping our
concerns to ourselves and hoping for things to change, as Winston Smith
did. If we truly wish to live in a free society, we must realize that no
politician or public figure can save us, even those we believe most in.
We can&#39;t expect the government or corporations or Oceania or the
Brotherhood to place our best interests atop their priority list. In
reality, it is and will forever be only up to us to save ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-i-recommend-this-to&#34;&gt;Who I recommend this to
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in politics:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; is a must read for anyone who
wishes to truly understand contemporary politics. Hopefully it&#39;ll also
put into perspective what real totalitarianism looks like and will
prompt you to defend yourself against it at its first sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in modern classics:&lt;/strong&gt; You&#39;ve probably read this
already if you identify with this description, but to those who
haven&#39;t, I trust you will not be disappointed. You will certainly get
to see a lot 20th-century influences on the story and background of
&lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>On Modern Incontinence</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/on-modern-incontinence/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 23:32:51 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/on-modern-incontinence/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/on-modern-incontinence/tinbergen.png" alt="Featured image of post On Modern Incontinence" /&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021. Me da un poco de cringe el estilo con el cual escribía antes, pero igual decido publicarla.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-ethology&#34;&gt;From ethology...
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 1940s, scientist Niko Tinbergen conducted several experiments on
the behavior of herring gulls. Adult herring gulls have a red dot on
their beaks, and newborn herring gulls will peck this dot to ask their
mother to regurgitate food. In one of his experiments, he designed a
fake cardboard beak, completely detached from a body, and offered it to
the chicks. He believed the chicks would ignore the dummy beak
altogether, but to his surprise, they pecked the red dot on this
cardboard beak just as much as they did the real one. Their attraction
to these red dots was clearly innate, not entirely learned. Tinbergen
then designed a series of beaks that changed the presentation of the dot
and studied the chicks&#39; reaction to them. Eventually, he designed a
beak that contained not one, but three unnaturally large and bright red
dots. When he presented it to them, the chicks turned frenetic, pecking
the beak as if it was the most joyous thing they were ever going to do.
Tinbergen studied other animals with similar innate attractions and
consistently found that he could exaggerate the characteristics of the
innately attractive to get the animals to react with an ardent desire
for it. He dubbed these &amp;quot;supernormal stimuli.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;centerimg&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;tinbergen.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;tinbergen.png&#34;
style=&#34;width: 50%;&#34; alt=&#34;Some of Tinbergen&amp;#39;s results.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some of Tinbergen&#39;s results.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this relevant? Well, the reactions of joyously desperate chicks
are quite adorable indeed... until you realize that there must be a
human equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-to-psychology&#34;&gt;... to psychology
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For millennia, we developed innate instincts and desires
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;#footnote-1&#34; &gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; that promoted our survival and reproduction. Salts,
fats, and sugars became attractive because they were rare but necessary
for survival. We developed a unique curiosity towards all kinds of
information because it all related to our real world and our survival in
it. Sex became stimulating because it promoted the passing of genes.
Even our attraction to that which is cute developed as a mechanism to
care for the young and vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in modern times, with the introduction of mass production and
growing consumer markets, companies began to realize, whether
consciously or unconsciously, that they too can easily appeal to our
innate desires to sell a product. The problem with this is that being
incontinent and excessively submitting to these impulses is a surefire
recipe for self-destruction. The modern diet is completely foreign to
what our ancestors ate, particularly because it is overloaded with
salts, fats, sugars, and all that which our bodies aren&#39;t prepared to
receive in large quantities. The advent of the digital age has allowed
us to overwhelm ourselves with vast amounts of information, most of
which will be completely unproductive and will ultimately subtract an
ungodly amount of time off of our lives, but will guarantee clicks,
views, and revenue nonetheless. And merely out of respect for myself,
and perhaps also out of concern for my sanity, I won&#39;t discuss the
abhorrent amount of time and money thrown into the deep, dark hole that
is &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; culture &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;#footnote-2&#34; &gt;\[2\]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, companies are not the main culprits. They only ever meet
demand. By desiring to have our innate desires satisfied at every
moment, &lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt; have created an environment that specializes and
continually becomes more efficient at doing so, and it won&#39;t hesitate
to push us to self-destruction if we so wish. If we instead wish to
avoid such a fate, then it is in our best interest we think twice about
following our desires. We shall here explore how mindlessly following
our impulses has fostered this dangerous environment and will continue
to strengthen it unless we stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-sell&#34;&gt;How to sell
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incontinence is an easy concept to understand. Just as an object in
motion remains in motion unless acted upon by another force, our
biological pull towards satisfying our innate desires will continue even
when it becomes counterproductive, unless we consciously attempt to stop
it. Traditional moral systems have historically been the force that
stopped this biological pull when it became self-destructive. Presently,
for reasons outside the scope of this article, these have greatly
diminished. The majority of people now have a vague understanding of or
even little interest in morality and distinguishing right from wrong,
and in this pop understanding of morality, incontinence falls
increasingly on the right side. If you&#39;re a company looking to sell a
product or a government looking to grow its economy, this is quite
convenient. Strong moral principles would simply sway demand against a
wide variety of consumptive habits. You can&#39;t sell sex to an abstainer
or alcohol to a teetotaler. Fortunately for you, however, your potential
consumers are already biologically primed towards fulfilling certain
innate desires as much as possible. You need only to offer them the
stimuli with which they can satisfy their craving, and then, with no
other act on your behalf, they will bite. Best of all, once they bite
it, few will hardly ever let go. Through habit their incontinence will
only reinforce itself, and they will return to you. The irony here is
that they will come to see their loyalty to you as an expression of
themselves, and some will even defend your business and your right to
operate in the &amp;quot;free&amp;quot; market, when in reality, their better judgment
overridden by their own incontinence, &lt;strong&gt;your own consumers have stopped
fully consenting to their consumption&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for you though, your products will almost certainly not be
the only fish in the sea. You will be fighting other companies for the
limited amount of time and money your potential customers have. To
ensure your continual survival, you must create products that
increasingly maximize customer satisfaction. Of course, you could try to
design a product that satisfies customers by actually providing a
benefit to them, undoubtedly some will, but if your goal still is to
maximize profits, then the sad reality is that in this world what
customers need does not outsell what customers want (or worse, what they
&lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; they need), and customers ardently want their innate desires
satisfied. Thus, anyone looking to acquire as much capital as possible
&lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; eventually have to betray its customers&#39; best interests and
push them towards incontinence. Now picture every company in the planet
trying to do so, and by mere Law of Least Effort, it becomes easier to
see why so many people today are slaves to their own impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;escape-the-supernormal&#34;&gt;Escape the supernormal
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What can be done about it? Frankly, I won&#39;t pretend I&#39;m too interested
in the large-scale transformation of our society. We all receive what we
dare to seek, and those who seek their own destruction will justly find
it. If, however, you belong to the few who seek to avoid it, then I can
at least offer some guidance on this less traveled path, taken from my
own personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our innate desires aren&#39;t inherently evil. Information, calories, and
even sexual gratification, though to a much lesser extent, are all part
of a good life. It is only when we corrupt or overuse these stimuli that
they become a force for evil in our lives. Engaging with stimuli this
way does feel pleasant, but, as you may already know, this will only
last a moment. The next dose of this stimulus will not be as pleasing,
and the more you try to chase its pleasure, the less it is within your
reach. What you may not know, however, is that as your brain adjusts
itself to the pleasure received from the stimulus, it becomes dependent
on it to function properly. In other words, the supernormal becomes
normal, the normal becomes tedious, and the challenging, where the
essence of life truly resides, becomes unbearable. Conversely, when one
rigorously abstains from corrupted and excessive pleasures, the normal
itself can become supernormally pleasing. Believe me, Reader, whatever
you seek out of life, it is not to be found in banal pleasures. Choose
to see the beauty in the normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Innate instincts, desires, cravings and
impulses are used interchangeably here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] These are only some of the negative
consequences of supernormal stimuli, and some of the bleaker ones at
that. See &lt;em&gt;Supernormal Stimuli&lt;/em&gt; below for more information on the true
harms of supernormal stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;see-also&#34;&gt;See also
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;atomic-habits-james-clear&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;, James Clear
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The book in which I first learned about supernormal stimuli. Note that
this book deals with the science behind behavior, not directly
supernormal stimuli. Still, I&#39;m sure those willing to break free from
incontinence will find this book to be of use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;supernormal-stimuli-how-primal-urges-overran-their-evolutionary-purpose-deirdre-barrett&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supernormal Stimuli: How Primal Urges Overran Their Evolutionary Purpose&lt;/em&gt;, Deirdre Barrett:
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;A book I stumbled upon while researching more on the topic. I cannot
recommend this enough if you wish to learn more about supernormal
stimuli themselves and their true potential for self-destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
