<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Religión ✝️ on Daniel Muñoz Lozano</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/tags/religi%C3%B3n-%EF%B8%8F/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Religión ✝️ on Daniel Muñoz Lozano</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 20:23:13 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://danielml.mx/tags/religi%C3%B3n-%EF%B8%8F/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Apología católica: refutaciones a argumentos comunes</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/apologia-catolica/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 20:23:13 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/apologia-catolica/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lo que procede es un repositorio de argumentos comunes en contra del catolicismo acompañados cada uno de una refutación definitiva, así como fuentes adicionales para quienes estén interesados en profundizar sobre dichas refutaciones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
### Contra el cristianismo

***

--&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;contra-el-catolicismola-iglesia-católica&#34;&gt;Contra el catolicismo/la Iglesia católica
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Iglesia católica y el catolicismo, dado que históricamente han sido el cuerpo de creyentes y de cristianos más grande en el mundo, son frecuente objeto de críticas tanto de no creyentes como de cristianos no católicos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;el-catolicismo-es-la-religión-que-más-ha-matado&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El catolicismo es la religión que más ha matado&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Este argumento, que a veces se presenta también como una crítica hacia la Iglesia católica, frecuentemente se &amp;ldquo;justifica&amp;rdquo; por las cruzadas y/o las inquisiciones. En realidad, el discurso popular sobre cómo operaron estas dos campañas está muy equivocado y lleno de mitos, producto de un currículum educativo que busca pintar la era medieval como &amp;ldquo;la era oscura&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Comenzando por las cruzadas, ... --&gt;
&lt;!-- Por otro lado, --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuando se habla de las inquisiciones bajo el contexto del discurso popular, frecuentemente se presenta esta idea de que estas campañas estuvieron llenas de juicios arbitrarios, tortura y gente quemada en la hoguera. La realidad no podría ser más diferente. La tarea principal de los inquisidores no era hacer sufrir a herejes, sino intentar salvar su alma y preservar así la unión de la Iglesia. Además, los juicios a los que eran sometidos los imputados eran extremadamente complejos, para nada arbitrarios, con sus propias reglas y procedimientos no del todo diferentes a las de nuestros juicios modernos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Para los imputados que llegaban a ser declarados como herejes, las sanciones aplicadas a través de los procedimientos inquisitivos medievales eran de índole penitente, no punitivo. Por ejemplo, el Tribunal del Santo Oficio, la institución que llevó a cabo la famosa Inquisición española, además de que no detenía a quienes se retractaban, aplicaba sanciones como asistir a misa con un cirio encendido en la mano junto con la realización de ayunos, el rezo de oraciones y el pago de multas para la blasfemia leve y auto de fe con soga al cuello y mordaza en la boca más la aplicación de cien azotes o el destierro para la blasfemia grave. Tanto el castigo corporal como el exilio forzado pueden sonar duros, sin embargo estos castigos eran más benignos a comparación de aquellos aplicados por las autoridades civiles, los cuales incluían desde la mutilación de la lengua hasta la pena de muerte. Hablando de, cabe destacar que los inquisidores no podían sentenciaban a muerte, sino que debían entregar a los herejes más persistentes a las autoridades seculares. Sobre todo, cabe destacar que las instituciones de la Inquisición eran aquellas más interesadas en el bien del hereje, a diferencia de los laicos, quienes sólo querían deshacerse del hereje antes de que la comunidad sufriera, y de los tribunales judiciales seculares, los cuales sólo buscaban castigar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incluso la Inquisición española, considerada popularmente la más celosa de todas, aun reconociendo el gran antisemitismo que la manchó y que culminó en la expulsión de los judíos del territorio español, hecho inconsistente con los principios de la Iglesia católica y por el cual Juan Pablo II se ha disculpado, fue acreedora de aproximadamente 3,000 muertes desde 1550 a 1800, las cuales desde luego son injustificables, mas demuestran un panorama muy diferente de la historia del que se presenta en el discurso popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lectura adicional&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peters, E. (1988). &lt;em&gt;Inquisition&lt;/em&gt;. Free Press. (principalmente pp. 64 - 67, 87)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.congreso.gob.pe/Docs/participacion/museo/Inquisicion/files/delitos-juzgados1.pdf&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Delitos juzgados por el Tribunal de la Inquisición&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carta al Card. Roger Etchegaray con motivo de la publicación de las Actas del Congreso Internacional sobre la Inquisición&lt;/em&gt;. (15 de junio de 2004). La Santa Sede. &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.vatican.va/content/john-paul-ii/es/letters/2004/documents/hf_jp-ii_let_20040615_simposio-inquisizione.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://www.vatican.va/content/john-paul-ii/es/letters/2004/documents/hf_jp-ii_let_20040615_simposio-inquisizione.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;yo-sólo-sigo-la-palabra-de-dios-no-las-tradiciones-de-los-hombres&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yo sólo sigo la Palabra de Dios, no las tradiciones de los hombres&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;La idea de que la fe cristiana es algo que se puede interpretar sólo a través de la escritura es un precursor a la racionalización de varios aspectos de nuestra sociedad. Si padeces de monocromatismo, pero estudias arduamente el color rojo y las propiedades del espectro de luz visible que lo constituyen, ¿realmente sabes lo que es el color rojo? ¿Es lo mismo leer y hasta ver fotos de Río de Janeiro que visitarlo? En un sentido epistemológico, sería difícil concluir que estos dos objetos de estudio se pueden conocer exclusivamente a través de las facultades lógico-racionales del ser humano. De la misma manera, el verdadero cristianismo (y la religión en general) no es algo que se comprende al creerlo tanto como se comprende al vivirlo, y como católicos debemos de vivirlo de la manera que Cristo nos enseñó, cosa que no hizo a través de libros, sino a través de sus obras, las cuales hoy hemos instituido como tradición. Sólo observa los desarrollos en las &amp;ldquo;iglesias&amp;rdquo; que, por tomar la escritura como fuente única de revelación, han abandonado la tradición.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por otro lado, este argumento viene cargado de una desconfianza inherente hacia el prójimo. A fin de ahorrarme una larga explicación hago la siguiente pregunta: si Cristo le confió las llaves de su Iglesia a un hombre, ¿bajo qué autoridad desconfías tú de ellos?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Purgatorio, Dante Alighieri (John Ciardi Translation) - Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/purgatorio-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:39:48 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/purgatorio-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021. Más que una crítica o reseña del poema, es un intento de vendérselo al público general. Me da un poco de cringe el estilo con el cual escribía antes, pero igual decido publicarla. Más importante, evité ahondar en el tema de la religión para hacer la publicación más acogedora para el público general, algo que nunca haría hoy.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!---
#![Purgatorio, Dante
#Alighieri](../assets/purgatorio_dante.jpg){.titleimg}
--&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Expect no more of me in word or deed: here your will is upright,
free, and whole, and you would be in error not to heed whatever your
own impulse prompts you to: lord of yourself I crown and mitre you.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Dante Alighieri, &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dante&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt; was written in 1320, and 700 years later its
ability to comprehensively cover all of human experience within a single
narrative remains unmatched. Drawing from the teachings of Thomas
Aquinas in his &lt;em&gt;Summa Theologiae&lt;/em&gt;, Dante outlines the universe as a
sphere, one in which God is its circumference and Satan its center.
Thus, the value of any given thing can be determined simply by
establishing how close it is to the boundaries of the sphere, and how
far away it is from its center. But this model is much more than that,
and its genius lies in the fact that it is capable of covering the order
of the literal universe, Christian experience and morality all within a
single model, outlined from the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;. It deals
with the physical understanding of the world, since (under the Ptolemaic
system of the times) the Earth was the center of the universe, which
meant that Hell was the origin point of the universe. It deals with
Christianity, because it takes Readers through the recognition of sin
(&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;), its complete rejection (&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;), and the soul&#39;s
ascent to God (&lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;). It deals with morality, because it explores
questions like what makes a bad man and what does it take to become a
good man. Above all, the &lt;em&gt;Commedia&lt;/em&gt; is comprehensive, since it manages
to encompass so much of what it means to be human, regardless of whether
these were born in antiquity, the Middle Ages, or the twenty-first
century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they climb the two ledges and seven cornices to reach the Earthly
Paradise, we yet again see all kinds of human faults, sometimes even on
par with what was found in the flames below, except these sinners
acknowledge, regret, and repent their mistakes, something which will
ultimately guarantee them an entrance into Paradise, no matter how
wicked their previous actions might have been. They suffer, but their
suffering stems from purification, which is temporary, not damnation,
which is eternal. Seeing all this pain, Dante (through Virgil) takes the
time to explain his theory on the nature of sin, in which he theorizes
all sin really stems from love: the Proud, Envious, and Wrathful have
corrupted their love of themselves to hate of others; the Slothful have
loved too little; and the Avaricious, Gluttonous, and Lustful have loved
immoderately. To reject sin, then, is to love truly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first steps are always the hardest, but as Dante distances himself
from the Earth and climbs the mountain by rejecting sin and taking in
virtue, his steps become lighter and lighter, until he finally reaches
the Earthly Paradise and prepares himself to rise towards the stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second part to Dante&#39;s great allegory does not disappoint. By now
most of the novelty has worn out and you&#39;re already accustomed to
Dante&#39;s world, style, and exposition, but they don&#39;t really cease to
be captivating. In the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;, through its characters, their
philosophy, and the very design of Purgatory, Dante yet again
demonstrates a side of pre-classical and medieval thought dearly missed
today. It presents a moral commentary on what is wrong, like the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, but it also emphasizes doing what is right. The Christian
roots of the poem are also more emphasized, particularly through the
virtue of the life of Mary, the Beatitudes sung by the Angels, and other
allegorical devices that urge the souls unto good. All in all, the
&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; accomplishes its goal of being a bridge between the
depravity of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; and the beauty of the &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main dynamic here is similar to what is seen in the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;: the
sinners suffer a punishment that relates to their sin. However, in the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; the punishment directly reflected the sin, whereas in the
&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; the punishment reverses the sin. For example, in the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; the Lustful were punished by being violently whirled through
the air, symbolizing how they followed their impulses on a whim. In the
&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; though, their impulses are symbolized by burning flames,
and they achieve penance by learning to stand calmly in them. Likewise,
the filthy marshes of the Styx hindered the Slothful&#39;s movement in the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, but here, they run around the cornice so vigorously that they
won&#39;t even stop to speak to Dante. You must remember Dante has given
symbolic meaning to nearly everything in the &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt;, and
these punishments are certainly no coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; also presents the dynamic of the whip and the rein. As
he climbs each cornice to meet the sinners, Dante is presented first
with a whip that urges the sinners unto emulation of virtue and then
with a reign that deters them from their sin, both symbolizing the same
tools utilized to control the behavior of a horse, respectively. These
devices, though presented in various forms, consist of historical
examples of great human virtue and fault particular to the sin of the
cornice on which the Poets find themselves, and the first examples of
great virtue always come from the life of Mary. For example, when the
Poets reach the first cornice, that of the Proud, they are presented
with three bas-reliefs carved in the perfect marble of the mountain&#39;s
inner cliff, the first of which depicts Mary&#39;s humble reaction upon the
Annunciation. After meeting the Proud and discovering their punishment,
Dante notices that the floor is carved with &lt;em&gt;thirteen&lt;/em&gt; examples of
destruction through pride, notable among these the tale of Arachne and
of Nimrod and his Tower of Babel. It is these devices which most
distinguish the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; from the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;. Hell is a destination
meant only to reflect the pain its inhabitants caused, but Purgatory is
instead a transitory phase, meant to teach and prepare the souls for
salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pleasant surprise within the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; is the fact that it contains
many medieval scientific, philosophical, and metaphysical theories, and
though at times they proved hard to follow to my modern mind, they were
exceptionally insightful. The most important of these is Virgil&#39;s
discourse on love, which as mentioned before is central to Dante&#39;s
understanding of sin. However, there are many other tangential
discourses that, though they aren&#39;t as crucial to the story and some
are even scientifically irrelevant today, they are still quite
thought-provoking. These are unfortunately too long to properly discuss
here, but as a quick overview, the Poets discuss anything from the
metaphysical faults of Averroism and Epicureanism to
Aristotelian/Aquinian ideas on conception and the birth of the human
soul. They greatly enrich the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s historic and cultural
content and yet again demonstrate how, perhaps contrary to popular
belief, the ancients and medievals weren&#39;t all ignorant and backwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-ciardis-translation&#34;&gt;A note on Ciardi&#39;s translation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; proved to be a more difficult read than I had
anticipated. It isn&#39;t incomprehensible by any means, but you do have to
pay extra attention to ensure that you don&#39;t miss out on any of
Dante&#39;s fine-carved details. The way in which the Poets utilize the
stars relative to the southern hemisphere of the world to describe
almost the exact hour of the day was particularly hard to grasp. Were it
not for the help of Ciardi, I certainly wouldn&#39;t have understood these
and other complexities presented in the canticle. Though I haven&#39;t
checked out the other translations, I can definitely vouch for this one.
Both it&#39;s notes and presentation are clear enough, but as with the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, the tone of the poem takes precedence, something I&#39;m
personally fine with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-i-recommend-this-to&#34;&gt;Who I recommend this to
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in morality:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; will yet again
enlighten those who are deeply interested in virtue. The whip is a most
useful compilation of great virtue from all periods of history, and many
other devices in the &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; also work as a commentary on virtue. I
invite you to ponder why Dante chose to place the suicide Cato as the
protector of Purgatory, yet Pierre delle Vigne suffers in the seventh
circle of Hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in Christianity:&lt;/strong&gt; As stated, the Christian
influence is more clear in this canticle as opposed to the previous one.
The &lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt; has all sorts of metaphors and references that allude
to Christianity (specifically Roman Catholicism, obviously) and the
history of the Church, from the color of the three steps taken at the
entrance of Purgatory to the Triumphal Chariot and the Heavenly Pageant.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Inferno, Dante Alighieri (John Ciardi Translation) - Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/inferno-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 23:50:11 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/inferno-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/inferno-thoughts/inferno_dante.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Inferno, Dante Alighieri (John Ciardi Translation) - Thoughts" /&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Esta es una de mis publicaciones viejas, escrita a finales del 2021. Más que una crítica o reseña del poema, es un intento de vendérselo al público general. Me da un poco de cringe el estilo con el cual escribía antes, pero igual decido publicarla. Más importante, evité ahondar en el tema de la religión para hacer la publicación más acogedora para el público general, algo que nunca haría hoy.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;But the stars that marked our starting fall away. We must go deeper
into greater pain, for it is not permitted that we stay.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;Dante Alighieri, &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dante&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt; was written in 1320, and 700 years later its
ability to comprehensively cover all of human experience within a single
narrative remains unmatched. Drawing from the teachings of Thomas
Aquinas in his &lt;em&gt;Summa Theologiae&lt;/em&gt;, Dante outlines the universe as a
sphere, one in which God is its circumference and Satan its center.
Thus, the value of any given thing can be determined simply by
establishing how close it is to the boundaries of the sphere, and how
far away it is from its center. But this model is much more than that,
and its genius lies in the fact that it is capable of covering the order
of the literal universe, Christian experience, and morality all within a
single model, outlined from the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;. It deals
with the physical understanding of the world, since (under the Ptolemaic
system of the times) the Earth was the center of the universe, which
meant that Hell was the origin point of the universe. It deals with
Christianity, because it takes Readers through the recognition of sin
(&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;), its complete rejection (&lt;em&gt;Purgatorio&lt;/em&gt;), and the soul&#39;s
ascent to God (&lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;). It deals with morality, because it explores
questions like what makes a bad man and what does it take to become a
good man. Above all, the &lt;em&gt;Commedia&lt;/em&gt; is comprehensive, since it manages
to encompass so much of what it means to be human, regardless of whether
these lived in antiquity, the Middle Ages or the twenty-first century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this model in mind, it is the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; which presents the
universe&#39;s damnation and wretches, that which is closest to the center.
Too involved in terrestrial affairs and thus found guilty of &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;,
Dante first finds himself helpless in the Dark Wood of Error. With the
help of his guide, Virgil the poet, he must venture into the Nine
Circles of Hell to know what it truly means to sin, so that he can later
know how to reject it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a journey that covers all faults in human behavior, and
the brilliance of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; (and of the &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt; as a
whole) is the fact that Dante does so by example, relating to the past,
present and future of humanity. He comments on the sins of historical
figures like Ulysses and Alexander the Great. He talks with Farinata on
the state of Florentine politics and its everlasting conflicts. He
cautions Pope Boniface VIII on the fate that awaits him and others like
him were they to continue perverting the holiness of the church. Through
the Nine Circles, each of these figures is masterfully placed according
to Dante&#39;s universal sphere, which itself comments on their moral
value. The &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, then, is an organization of all wrong that men do.
It is the journey of Dante, yes, but the true goal of Dante (the
narrator) is to take &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; on the same journey, so that you too can
learn to recognize and reject the wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; has been a teacher to me. Generally I think people do know
how the people of the Middle Ages lived and died, including myself, but
it wasn&#39;t until after the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; that I began to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;
they lived the way they did. From the faint light in Dark Wood of Error
to the perversion of the Holy Trinity in the ninth and final circle of
Hell, Dante has packed the poem with all sorts of metaphors, symbols and
historical references that reveal to the modern Reader what went on
inside the heads of medieval men, including both the sharpest minds and
the average peasants&#39;. In essence, most people who have not read the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; can expect to have their views on Christianity, morality,
antiquity and the Middle Ages built anew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By categorizing sin into a set of nine descending circles, Dante draws a
critique on the darker side of morality, on what is irrefutably wrong,
even outside of Christian doctrine. It is a critique I learned a lot
from, and think many could benefit from too. Most of all, this
categorization of sin from worse to worst allows us not to learn, but to
&lt;strong&gt;recognize&lt;/strong&gt; what we already know deep down: we are all capable of
enacting great evil, including you, me, and your average Joes and Janes.
The poem forces you to recognize all sorts of evils, sometimes those
that you yourself have not only enacted, but taken pleasure in doing so.
One must, however, attune themselves to the medieval understanding of
evil, which for them was individual and personal, not entirely
collective and based upon how harmful an action is towards others.
Gluttony, for example, often harms no one other than the perpetrator,
yet it is still an evil action. Likewise, methodical fraud is found
below incontinent violence in Hell because it involves a greater usage
of free will. Crime (the modern moral compass) involves destruction. Sin
involves first and foremost self-destruction. In the end, all evil we
enact is only ever reflected unto ourselves, and Dante makes a clear
point that this is true in both life and afterlife, not merely a matter
of divine punishment. The Law of Hell dictates that it is the sinners
who in life have &lt;strong&gt;voluntarily chosen&lt;/strong&gt; their own eternal suffering.
Thus, as they harmed themselves in life, they harm themselves eternally
in the afterlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How this Law manifests itself throughout the poem is perhaps the richest
and most stimulating metaphor in the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, especially because Dante
utilizes real or mythological figures to devise clever punishments that
reflect on the nature of the sinners&#39; sin. Take, for example, the
Violent Against Neighbor, found in the seventh circle of Hell. Their
torment is that they are thrown into a river of boiling blood, symbol of
the blood they spilled in the physical world. Yet not all suffer
equally, for every sinner&#39;s suffering is perfectly attuned to their
wretchedness. The pettier get to be only ankle deep in the river, while
the bloodthirsty like Alexander the Great drown with the blood up to
their eyelashes. Dante&#39;s clever punishments keep you on the edge,
curious to know how the sins of the sinners will turn on them and become
their punishment. You know now how the violent are punished, but how do
you suppose lustful have their sin reflected on them? The gluttonous?
The greedy? Your interest is piqued, isn&#39;t it, Reader?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, while there is great value in the references to great
historical figures such as Alexander, Cleopatra and Caesar, there is
something equally charming about Dante&#39;s more personal references to
the characters of his Florence. Every medieval character Dante meets has
a story to tell, one that places us right in Dante&#39;s time and allows us
to learn more about how different the world was back then. Sometimes you
get to learn about the politics of the time, like stereotypes of the
city of Bologna being one of panderers and seducers and Lucca, of
grafters, and others you get to learn about the personal lives of its
people, like the woeful tale of Ugolino and his death, but they all
allow you to get a sense of what life was like in the then-present, of
who were the people of the Medieval Ages and what they stood (and fell)
for. The &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s masterful presentation of antiquity, morality and
Christianity already made it rich in substance, but these more personal
references make the poem that much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know my writing could never do the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; the justice it deserves,
so while I&#39;m about to be more specific with whom I recommend the poem
to in a moment, I actually think anyone can benefit from reading the
&lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;. The past is truly an alien civilization, its wisdom is almost
completely disconnected from modern thought and is, in many ways, simply
better than it. I am of the belief that the seeds of our future are sown
in our past, and the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; is yet another reason to believe it to be
so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-ciardis-translation&#34;&gt;A note on Ciardi&#39;s translation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Ciardi&#39;s translation in particular, I can vouch for its quality and
do highly recommend it, though it would be imprudent to compare it to
other translations without having read these. I will say, however, that
from the quick research I did before choosing this version, Ciardi&#39;s
translation appears to prioritize the poem&#39;s phonetics over its literal
translation when compared to others and also stands out for its notes. I
can attest to both of these facts, as though I&#39;m used to prose and may
have felt a bit disoriented at times, the poem&#39;s beauty is always
clearly front and center, and any misinterpretation is always cleared up
in the excellent notes anyways. In any case, the particular quirks
between translations aren&#39;t as important as it is to actually read any
version of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt; (and the &lt;em&gt;Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt;, for that matter).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-i-recommend-this-to&#34;&gt;Who I recommend this to
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in morality and religion:&lt;/strong&gt; It comes as no surprise
that these readers are often the first to pick up the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;. Rest
assured, this poem has a lot to teach you about zeal, morality, and
their dark counterparts, and you will undoubtedly benefit from its
wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers interested in history:&lt;/strong&gt; There is something special about
getting to see Julius Caesar, Homer, Socrates, Cleopatra and many other
historical figures within the same narrative. History aficionados will
undoubtedly enjoy reading Dante&#39;s profound knowledge on the subject
throughout the pages of the &lt;em&gt;Inferno&lt;/em&gt;, perhaps learning a thing or two
along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>El salón de fama de Dios</title>
        <link>https://danielml.mx/posts/el-salon-de-fama-de-dios/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 09:58:18 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://danielml.mx/posts/el-salon-de-fama-de-dios/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://danielml.mx/posts/el-salon-de-fama-de-dios/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post El salón de fama de Dios" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lo que procede es mi intento de traducir al español uno de mis poemas contemporáneos favoritos, &lt;em&gt;God&amp;rsquo;s Hall of Fame&lt;/em&gt;, tradicionalmente adjudicado a Alf Hutchinson, mantentiendo una métrica decasílaba constante y sin rima. Quizá para la próxima intente traducir la versión extendida, narrada por Jim Caviezel en &lt;em&gt;The Sound of Freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#39;text-align: center;&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tu nombre podría estar ausente&lt;br&gt;
del salón de fama de este mundo.&lt;br&gt;
Podrías ser tan desconocido,&lt;br&gt;
pocos tu nombre conocerán.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La fama y la fortuna te eluden,&lt;br&gt;
pues sólo a unos pocos se conceden,&lt;br&gt;
Pero si al Señor amas y sirves,&lt;br&gt;
buenas noticias hay para ti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este salón de fama perdura&lt;br&gt;
sólo mientras el mundo perdure,&lt;br&gt;
pero considera que eterno es&lt;br&gt;
el salón de la fama de Dios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tu nombre tener inscrito arriba&lt;br&gt;
enormemente más grandioso es&lt;br&gt;
que todos los salones del mundo&lt;br&gt;
y cada estrella hecha por el hombre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pronto olvida la gente del mundo&lt;br&gt;
a aquellos héroes del pasado.&lt;br&gt;
Ellos aplauden hasta que caes,&lt;br&gt;
y solamente eso es lo que duras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pero no el Señor, pues nunca olvida,&lt;br&gt;
y verás que en Su salón de fama,&lt;br&gt;
por el hecho de creer en Su Hijo,&lt;br&gt;
inscrito tu nombre encontrarás.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Te digo amigo, no cambiaría&lt;br&gt;
mi nombre, por pequeño que sea,&lt;br&gt;
inscrito aun pasando las estrellas&lt;br&gt;
en ese alto salón celestial&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por cada nombre famoso aquí,&lt;br&gt;
o la gloria que juntos comparten.&lt;br&gt;
Prefiero un donnadie ser aquí&lt;br&gt;
¡y mi nombre ahí arriba encontrar!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Película sobrevalorada por cierto, pero al menos el poema es bueno.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
